<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves for nevvters: or, The check cause cure of halting. With 31 doores of hope for the good successe of the publick cause of the kingdome. / Delivered in a sermon, November 27. 1644: in the Colledge of Glocester, before that valiant and vigilant governour Colonell Massy, being the day of publick humiliation. By Walter Powell, M.A. vicar of Standish. See the contents after the epistle.</title>
            <author>Powell, Walter, b. 1590 or 91.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E474_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204200</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863870</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E474[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves for nevvters: or, The check cause cure of halting. With 31 doores of hope for the good successe of the publick cause of the kingdome. / Delivered in a sermon, November 27. 1644: in the Colledge of Glocester, before that valiant and vigilant governour Colonell Massy, being the day of publick humiliation. By Walter Powell, M.A. vicar of Standish. See the contents after the epistle.</title>
                  <author>Powell, Walter, b. 1590 or 91.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "check cause cure" are enclosed in brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 30th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116086:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEVVES FOR NEWTERS: OR, The
<list>
                  <item>Check</item>
                  <item>Cauſe</item>
                  <item>Cure</item>
               </list>
of Halting.</p>
            <p>With 31 Doores of Hope for the good ſucceſſe of the publick cauſe of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Delivered in a Sermon, November 27. 1644: in the Colledge of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> before that valiant and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Governour Colonell <hi>Maſſy,</hi> being the day of publick Humiliation.</p>
            <p>By WALTER POWELL, M. A. Vicar of Standiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſt neutrale genus ſignans rem non animatam.</hi> See the Contents after the Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116086:2"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured, Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall MASSEY, one of the Members of the Honorable Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Renowned Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O none doth this Sermon more properly belong, now prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then to your ſelfe, that heard it preached. After the relation of which newes againſt Newters, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned beyond my deſert and expectation publick thanks in the face of that populous Congregation.</p>
            <p>In thoſe then ſiding-unſiding times, this Text at that time was ſeaſonable I yet beleeve; though the ſight of my perſon in the Pulpit, at that time, formidable perhaps to ſome there, that had never heard me preach in their whole life. One of which departing out of the then Congregation, had he ſtayed, you told me, at your Table, might have ſuſpected himſelfe to be like the Hedge-bogge, I mentioned in my Sermon.</p>
            <p>The truth of many of the particulars mentioned in my preceding Epiſtle, you know to be true: but I ſhall manifeſt the whole to be ſo, if from the Honorable Houſe I obtain my conceived juſt requeſt, to have liberty to examine the combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and unjuſt proceedings of my malevolent, yet potent Committee-adverſary.</p>
            <p>Sir, you beleeved and ſubſcribed as much under your hand, that this Sermon was preached with much zeale againſt newtralitie; and in that ſubſcription (out of which I tranſcribe your own words at this inſtant, having the copy now at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> before me) you are pleaſed to approve of my (then) Doores of Hope for the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Parliament cauſe.</p>
            <p>In reſpect whereof you ſay further, I then had merited, and you beleeved, I ſhould find favour from this Parliament. You beleeved alſo, I had hard meaſure in my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe; and that this Sermon was ſome occaſion of my harder uſage, though indeed the two poynts (here touched) concerning Countrey-Committees, and flattering Miniſters, were not then bandled.</p>
            <p>If you enquire after newes out of your once <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire,</hi> I beleeve many that were but Newters in your time of abode there, are in heart now most ſtrong Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants,
<pb facs="tcp:116086:3"/>perhaps it is becauſe too much ſavour hath been extended towards them. The inlarged vaſt difference betweene thoſe at home that ſhould be reconciled friends, to oppoſe the common foe, makes many continue in a balting condition e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this day: And thoſe that were then ſeeming friends, to become now ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the common cauſe. That which was a fiction long agoe, ſeems to be now put in action.</p>
            <p>The Eagle (they ſay) bad a neſt on the top of the Tree, where ſhe had her young; the Beare had her Den, where ſhe had her whelps under the bottome of the Tree: The Cat had liberty to run from the bottome to the top, and to be a ſpeedy meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger between the Eagle and the Beare; tells the Eagle if ſhe flye from her neſt, the Beare waits to devoure her brood, and tells the Beare, if ſhe peepout of her Den, the Eagle will make a prey of her whelps. And thus perſwades them to keep cloſe in their holes, to the ſtarving of themſelves and their young ones, that all might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a prey to the crafty Cat. My profeſſed Malignants, and their Neighbour Newters (Gallemoufrean, hotch-potch-ambo-dexters, time-ſerving weathercock-linſee-wolſie-turn-coats, Jack on both ſides, or rather Nick on no ſide) perſwade the people in theſe moſt dangerous times, that the rigid Presbyterians will keep them in more ſlavery then ever Biſhops Government did: and that the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents will have all things common amongst them. And this is the deepeſt policie that all the Devils in Hell could ever invent to prevaile with people to ſit ſtill, at <hi>Marcus Cato,</hi> and <hi>Metius Suffetius,</hi> the <hi>Succoits,</hi> and the <hi>Meroſhites</hi> did, that ſo profeſſed Malignants might have the more eaſie opportunity to make the inhabitants of the land to be made meat for their gaping mouthes.</p>
            <p>If God ever joyn the faithfull of the people together in a firme and ſincere uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to preſerve the Kingdome from ſlavery and ruine, he is little better then a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, I am ſure no friend to the Kingdome, that endeavours to rend peoples affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions aſunder.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am in my journey, therefore make bold to break off abruptly, leaving you to the direction of him who hath been your protection. Both which ſhall be the ſubject of the prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your much obliged SUFFERING Servant, WALTER POWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116086:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, the Lords and Commons aſſembled in PARLIAMENT; The Author imploreth freedome from Halting, Wiſdome in diſcerning, Grace and Glory for Perſevering.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable and Noble Senators,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>ui advos audent ſcribere, ignorant magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem, qui non audent, humanitatem.</hi> That which none are willing to owne, moſt men have endeavoured to embrace, and practice, <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> All men (if you will beleeve them) will be for God at their death, here and there one that will ſtand for his cauſe in the time of their life, When in theſe wars men were <hi>called to come forth, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> &amp; moſt meal mouth'd Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had their lips ſealed, and falſ-hearted people ſtood with their hands in their pockets, not with their feet in the <hi>gap, to make up the hedge before the Lord, that he might not deſtroy the land;</hi> then this Sermon in a publick place, before an eminent and publick perſon<note n="*" place="margin">Colonell <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and faithfull Governer of <hi>Gloceſter</hi>
               </note>, (once a member of this honorable <hi>Houſe</hi>) was preached; whoſe eye-obſerving diligent attention
<pb facs="tcp:116086:4"/>in hearing, publick reſpect and thanks in the face of that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous audience, immediatly after the delivery of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, are not the cauſes of the publiſhing hereof; but the diſregard of one of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> Committee in his uncivill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of the Congregation, before ever hee heard me either pray or preach, preſſed mee to commit this to the Preſſe: who ſhewed diſreſpect to the Sermon, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſake, when as he ſhould have manifeſted reſpect to the perſon for the Sermons ſake, There was no neceſſity (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve no) (I am ſure no humanity) for any of that Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee to cauſe a Sermon to be preached in another Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at that very inſtant by that very Miniſter, who then was ſick, and deſired to be eaſed from preaching that turn and time, in the Colledge of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi> When this Sermon at a publique faſt was preached, (how ever it may ſeem now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable, coming ſo late to the preſſe) was welcome (I am confident) to moſt that heard it delivered in the pulpit. The Sermon, I confeſſe, was ſomewhat long, it was the buſineſſe of the day that then required it. But what is added in the point of Countrey Committees, was not then ſpecified; for I then imagined, that ſuch qualified perſons were not <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum naturae.</hi> And what is inſerted touching flattering Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that have betrayed the truſt that God and man have committed to them, was alſo unhandled; both which are proper to the ſubject here in diſcourſe, as main cauſes of the people halting between thoſe two different opinions, in the then common Cauſe of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia dat qui juſta negat,</hi> he that denieth that which is juſt, gives liberty to ſpeak any thing.</p>
            <p>If I have unjuſtly blamed one of the ſaid <hi>Committee</hi> (whoſe advice, as another <hi>Achitophel</hi> in thoſe parts, was ſo highly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of, as if a man had enquired at the Oracle of God) in that cenſure againſt me, before any witneſſes in that cauſe were examined by me, (though many of the Committe, by
<pb facs="tcp:116086:4"/>the procurement of one, certified under their hands the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as groſſe untruths, as if they had ſubſcribed that there is no light in the Sunne, nor heat in the fire, or that the <hi>Pope</hi> in perſon ſits daily in the <hi>Parliament Houſe</hi>) to the great loſſe of my livelihood, danger of my life, and diſhonour of the Parliament (had I not been relieved) let me ſuffer more in name, perſon, eſtate: Whoſoever knowes what hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto me, as many thouſands have heard, may gueſſe that I am neceſſitated to publiſh this <hi>Newes for Newters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that was once an eye-hearer of this Sermon, beleeved in heart, and ſubſcribed with hand, that I had the harder u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for the meſſage ſake, elſe that Committee man could not have ſo poſted out of the Colledge, when hee ſaw me in the Pulpit, unleſſe he had almoſt as much feared my meſſage (whom he never heard in publique in his life) as hee dreaded the roaring of the Cannon when he haſted out of the Citie immediatly before the Kings Army came to beſiege the ſame.</p>
            <p>What in publick I have ſpoken, done and ſuffered for the common Cauſe, hundreds have, and thouſands will teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: yet all praying, preaching, doing and ſuffering, muſt be buried under the beaſtlike skin of Scandall, to provoke and ſatisfie the greedy appetites of a New Committee man, an old Hangman, and a poſted Malignant, and a profeſſed Newter.</p>
            <p>I attended eleven dayes (during part of which time this newes was related) to ſee theſe hideous <hi>November-Articles</hi> I was to anſwer, yet could not all that time have a ſight of them, till that quick-ſighted much knowing juſtice, Colonel <hi>Bromwich</hi> told the Committee it was a ſhame to make me wait ſo long for the ſaid Articles. Then had I <hi>December-Articles,</hi> and thoſe concerned the Committee themſelves, becauſe they would be ſure to ſtrike a deadly blow againſt ſuch a Traytor. Then had I <hi>January-Articles</hi> preferred, and
<pb facs="tcp:116086:5"/>had I not appealed to this Honorable Aſſembly, I thinke I ſhould have had <hi>February-Articles,</hi> and ſo <hi>ad infinitum;</hi> that no moneths malice might be left unattempted to ruine him, whom the Parliament had publiſhed and declared, 1643. to honour.</p>
            <p>I was accounted by the <hi>Plundering</hi> warrants of Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, at the ſiege of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> an aider to the Rebels, meaning this Parliament: and by the ſaid warrants had my goods and Cattell taken away; That the ſame Parliament Committee, after I had appealed to the Parliament it ſelfe from them, <hi>they under their hands denying me Copies of depoſitions, taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and denying me to be preſent at the examination of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> was by the teſtimony of divers members of this great Aſſembly, deemed unparallel.</p>
            <p>As theſe things with the effects thereof, to me have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a burthen (almoſt) intollerable (the ſcarre of diſcredit it being incurable) ſo to all men may ſeeme incredible, that a conſtant ſider with the Parliament ſhould, unheard, out of his living be ejected, and himſelf and his family be to all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery expoſed, (when that right-diſcerning, and Parliament-promiſes-promoting Juſtice, Mr. <hi>Anthony Clifford,</hi> oppoſed in my abſence, the reſt of my ruining unjuſt Judges:) If I ſhould forbeare, the ſtones would cry aloud, in the eyes and eares of the world, for juſtice againſt this matchleſſe, malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous abominable cenſure.</p>
            <p>But the bleſſing of the Lord for ever be and abide on the heads and hearts of the honorable Committee for plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Miniſters; and in particular, on Mr. <hi>Millington,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rouſe,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Hazelrig,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tate,</hi> who oft afforded me patience, audience, countenance. If I ſhould repeat every member of that Committee, I might ſeeme to flatter: if I ſhould not mention you, I ſhould ſurely be ungratefull: My Countrey-man Mr. <hi>Pury</hi> was one of the firſt that after my freezing and long waiting, broke the Ice for my return: and
<pb facs="tcp:116086:5"/>Mr. <hi>Edward Stephens,</hi> and others, quickly apprehended, and couragiouſly reported the injuſtice of the proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: Whereupon I had an Order of reſtitution to my Priviledges and Arreares, till the matter be heard; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which Order of Reſtitution, that active Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee man hath been an Inſtrument to place (for my ſupplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) in my Chappell, to enjoy thoſe profits that are almoſt the one halfe of my little livelihood, a Miniſter that hath been taken in Armes againſt the Parliament, and hath beene ejected out of his living in <hi>Monmouth-ſhire, for being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious againſt his neighbours, a common Drunkard, a Rayler a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament:</hi> who alſo ſaid, ſince he was obtruded on my Cure, <hi>a Cavaliere I was, a Cavaliere I am, and ſo I will continue.</hi> Whether ſuch a Committee man in permitting ſuch a Malignant Miniſter, that hath been ſo often active in Armes, to be placed and officiate within three miles of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> Garriſon, hath thereby promoted the honour of the Parliament, and the ſafety of that Citie, let all men judge: If I have been illegally proceeded againſt by this principall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in that Committee, as my worthy, conſtant, free and faithfull friend, Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> hath by tongue and pen maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I ſhall account it a great honour from this Honorable Aſſembly, to have an Order and Commiſſion to ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, I ſhall nominate, to examine all proceedings of this Committee man, and the combination of ſuch malignant, malicious perſons, as have been unjuſt practizers againſt me, that I may receive ſuch reparations from them, as the merits of my cauſe, and their cruelty ſhall require. All which is committed to the ſerious conſideration of this honorable Senate, for the relief of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithfull Servant, yet</hi> ſuffering <hi>ſupplicant,</hi> WALTER POWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:116086:6"/>
            <head>Doctrines deduced.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>DOct. 1.</hi> It is a great ſin and ſhame to halt between God and Baal. Truth and Error. pag. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Thoſe that are good, will ſhew zeale for God. pag. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> People continue long in a lingring condition, notwithſtanding long and ſharp reprehenſion. pag. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Many are yet to ſeek who is the true God. pag. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> God alone is to be followed. pag. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Men are oft convicted before they are once converted. pag. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The firſt Doctrine proſecuted.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſes. 1.</hi> Of Information. <hi>2.</hi> Reprehenſion of Newters. <hi>3.</hi> The Cauſes with the cure of Halting. pag. <hi>7, 8, 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cauſe 1.</hi> Becauſe many members of the Parliament have diſerted the Parliaments cauſe. pag. <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The greateſt part of the Great ones have adhered to the adverſe part. pag. <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Miſpriſion of prerogative. pag. <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Moſt of people ſiding with the contrary, rather than the Kingdomes Cauſe. pag. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The great preſſure by payments. pag. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Feare of being plundered, pag. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Selfe-ſeeking, with neglect of the publick. pag. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeſire of change for feare of changing for the worſe. pag. <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Eſtimation of Parliament-power too great. pag. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Injuſtice and oppreſſion by Countrey-Committees. pag. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Flattery in, and diviſions between Miniſters. pag. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Doubt of the ſucceſſe of the cauſe in hand, make men halt herein. pag. <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Which laſt rub is removed, in briefly opening many Doores of Hope for the good ſucceſſe of the Common Cauſe. pag. <hi>35, 36, 37,</hi> to the end.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata's. For <hi>1</hi> Kings <hi>19.</hi> read <hi>18.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PAG. 1. in the magent, for uſe 1. and uſe 2. read verſe. p. 2. l. 5. for purſuane, r. perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. p. 2. for uſe r. verſe 4. and verſe 5. p. 2. l. 27. for Daobolum, r. Da obolum. p. 3. l. 19. for liezure, r leiſure. p. 3. l. 21. make a period between yea, and plain. p. 5. l. 3. for there r. theſe. p. 7. l. 23. for nor, r no p. 7. l. 35, after Paſtors make no period. p. 8. l. 18. in Margent, read uſe 2. p. 8. l. 22. for defendant, r defendit. p 14. l. 2. after ſharp, but very exemplary, put preſident. p. 15. l. 7. for ſtrangely r. ſtrongly. p. 16. l. 7 for the r. this p. 20. l. 27. for belluae r. Bellua. p. 20. l. 31. ptt out they, before ſay p. 26. l. 23. r. an after. p 29. l. 7. for torror <hi>r.</hi> terrour. p. 29. l. 9. for have <hi>r.</hi> had. for I think ſome Committe-men have bought more land ſince (then they ſold before) they were preferred to their Committeſhips. p. 31. l. 3. unto ſeduce ſtrayable people, adde, and peſecute Gods zealous miniſters. P. 38. l. 2. for he, <hi>r.</hi> Shammah. p, 42. l. 4. for reigne, <hi>r.</hi> rejoyce. p. 47. l. l. 34. for And, <hi>r.</hi> Are theſe duties. p. 48. l. 11. in ſtead of an evill cauſe, read, and will not he regard the voyce, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116086:6"/>
            <head>Newes for Neuters. OR, The Checke, Cauſe, and cure of <hi>HALTING.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 King 19.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And Elijah came unto all the people, and ſaid, How long halt ye betweene two opinions? If the Lord be God, follow him, but if Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, then follow him: and the people anſwered him not a word.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Fountain, or Well-head is farre, from whence floweth my Text: It is twenty ſteps off.<note place="margin">Judges 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave with <hi>Gideons</hi> Souldiers to lap a mouthfull as I run along by the ſtreame: Before I come to my ſtation, to view theſe words.</p>
            <p>This Chapter containes a Dialogue, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of many hiſtoricall paſſages.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Betweene the Lord and <hi>Eliah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Goe ſhew thy ſelfe to</hi> Ahab.</p>
            <p>Meane ones muſt not be affraid to deliver meſſages to the Mighty.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Ch. 17.2.5. Chap. 19. <hi>Doct.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eliah's</hi> ready obedience to the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>There is a time when <hi>Eliah</hi> muſt flye from <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Jezabell,</hi> if the Lord command him.</p>
            <p>Where God hath a Tongue to ſpeake, there man muſt have an eare to heare.</p>
            <p>There is a time to flye,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> and a time to ſtay; God may be glorified ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more by flying, than by ſtaying.</p>
            <p>When the force of the enemie may be too ſtrong,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.22.</note> and the Faith of the perſecuted may be too weake. <hi>When they perſecute you in one City, flye into another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116086:7"/>When you may glorifie God more in the place to which, then in the place from which you flye. You may take leave to depart from men, when firſt in given by God.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this counſell is given,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>(When they perſecute you into one City, flye into another.)</hi> After the command of purſuance.</p>
            <p>Mercies and miſeries are oft mixed together, Chequer worke is a daily Trade in theſe times. God promiſed raine when there was a great famine in <hi>Samaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great peace may enſue theſe great wars.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>And</hi> Ahab <hi>called</hi> Obadiah <hi>who feared God greatly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some raiſed up to be good in a generall Apoſtacy from God;<note place="margin">Doct.</note> elſe woe were to the Kingdome in theſe times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obadiah</hi> tooke a hundred Prophets,<note place="margin">Vſe 4.</note> and hid them by fifty in a Cave. Wherein appeared his zeale and care.</p>
            <p>This hath encouraged <hi>Londoners</hi> to entertaine Strangers in theſe times of danger.</p>
            <p>The names and actions of the godly ſhall be had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A groane ſhall be regiſtred.</p>
            <p>A cup of cold water remembred.</p>
            <p>Teares ſhall be botled, and ſhall not blood be booked?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He feedeth them with Bread and Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that feare God,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> he will ſhew ſuccour to them in time of need.</p>
            <p>Gods deareſt Saints may be brought to a morſell of bread,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> to a cup of cold water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Belliſſarius</hi> a great Commander came (being blinde) to ſtand on the high way, with a <hi>Daobolum Belliſſario.</hi> Give one half-penny to poor blinde <hi>Belleſſarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another wrote to his friend to ſend to him a Spunge, a Harpe, and a loafe of bread.</p>
            <p>A ſpunge to dry up his teares; A harpe to ſolace his minde; And a loaf of bread to ſatisfie his hunger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ahab's</hi> command to <hi>Obadiah</hi> for the preſervation of graſſe for the lives of the Horſes and Mules:<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Was <hi>Ahab</hi> ſo carefull for graſſe? how carefull ſhould our King be for Corne and Cattle, Laws and liberties, perſons and Kingdome, Bodies and Soules of living men, that all be not loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ahab</hi> was carefull to ſeeke for ſuſtenance though it was (upon an if ſo be) a peradventure to finde or not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioabs</hi> reſolution was, <hi>Let us be valiant for our people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>and for the Cities of our God, and let him doe as ſeemeth him good.</hi> Let men doe as God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and let God doe as he hath decreed. How carefull, how earneſt ſhould men be for Grace, for heaven?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116086:7"/>Theſe may be ſought and found,<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> upon certainties without peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſhews their policie and care; the King to goe one way, and <hi>Obadiah</hi> another. Policy to direct the beſt courſe, and care to put it in execution.</p>
            <p>Policy may be uſed, ſo piety be not ſuppreſſed.<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods providence ſeene</hi> in bringing together <hi>Eliah</hi> and <hi>Obadiah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Behold,</hi> Eliah <hi>was in the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> went to ſeeke his Fathers Aſſes, and found a Kingdome; <hi>Obadiah</hi> went to ſeeke water and graſſe, and behold he findes a way and meanes to bring ſalvation to people. He went in obedience to the command of a King on Earth, and meetes with an unerring command of the King of Heaven.<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Gods providence over-rules all actions,<note place="margin">Text.</note> perſons, times, things, <hi>[fell downe on his face, &amp;c.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Meſſengers of God find favour from thoſe that are good.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>1.</hi> Doct. <hi>2.</hi> Doct. <hi>3</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Good Chriſtians will know one another in times of adverſity. Good men deſire to be reſolved of their doubts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obadiah</hi> thought that it was <hi>Eliah,</hi> yet labours to be aſſured thereof. And he anſwered,<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> I am; <hi>Goe tell, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliah</hi> had no French complementall formallity in his mouth, of <hi>your humble ſervant, Sir</hi> (as men now a days, who have more liezure and skill in promiſing the duty of Servants, then love and wil in performing the office of friends:) but <hi>Engliſh</hi> down-right reallity; he anſwers, yea plain diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries are moſt pleaſing.<note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>Eliah</hi> reveales the naked truth; here no equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is ſtudyed or practiſed.</p>
            <p>There needs no Complement with men when Commands are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from God.</p>
            <p>He had an Errand from the God of heaven, to a King on earth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gives him a ſhort, quicke, plaine, pithy anſwer.</p>
            <p>From verſ. 9. to 15. we ſee <hi>Obadia's</hi> feare, with the many reaſons of his refuſall for delivering the Meſſage. <hi>The Spirit may be willing, when the fleſh is weake.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliah</hi> will ſhew himſelfe to <hi>Ahab</hi> come what ever will come on it.<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The righteous are as bold as a Lyon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Obadiah</hi> went to meete <hi>Ahab.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> Care of Cattell muſt be neglected, when Gods will is to be performed.<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Ahabs</hi> willing journey to meete <hi>Eliah.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Gods worke ſhall be furthered whether man will or no.<note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>Obadiah</hi> went to further Gods worke. <hi>Ahab</hi> to ſatisfie his owne luſt, and to further the Devills worke.<note place="margin">Doct.</note> Man purpoſeth, but the Lord diſpoſeth of the purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. He can bring light out of darkneſſe, good out of evill; as the Bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney out of weeds.</p>
            <p>The ſharp and ſhort ſalutation that <hi>Ahab</hi> gives to <hi>Eliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Art thou hee that art the troubler of</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116086:8"/>Prophets commonly cenſured for Authors and Fautors of Troubles.<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliah's</hi> anſwer to <hi>Ahabs</hi> accuſation.<note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> Where reade,
<list>
                  <item>1. Vindication of himſelfe, <hi>I am not.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The juſt Taxation of the King. <hi>It is thou and thy Fathers houſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Many ſee faults in others, not in themſelves.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </item>
               <item>2. Kings may be blamed.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </item>
               <item>3. Man is the author of his owne miſery.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </item>
               <item>4. Diſobedience to God the cauſe of all miſery to man.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> When men forſake the fountaine, they dig to themſelves pits that will hold no water.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Prophet having told the King what he had done againſt him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 19, 20</note> tells him what he muſt doe for the Lord; <hi>Eliah</hi> came with a meſſage from the God of heaven, therefore commands <hi>Ahab,</hi> and directs him.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt appeare on mount Carmel before this deſpiſed Prophet.</p>
            <p>God can and will honour thoſe whom the wicked of the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, diſgrace, and perſecute.<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The 450. Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> muſt come with the 400. Chaplains of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All things and perſons muſt ſubject themſelves to heavens decree.<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>God can and will call to an account notwithſtanding Prophets,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> people goe along in their ſins.</p>
            <p>Thou thoughtſt I was like unto thee:<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> 
               <hi>but I will ſet thy ſinnes in order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pleaſure of ſin may goe before, when paine for ſin ſhall follow after.</p>
            <p>If the paine of the head-ach were before the pleaſure of the wine, none would be drunke.</p>
            <p>If ſinnes wages were fore-ſeene, the worke thereof would not be ſo willing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So</hi> Ahab <hi>ſent unto all the Children of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and gathered the Prophets to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to Mount Carmel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ahab</hi> executeth <hi>Eliah's,</hi> or rather the Lords commands, and that ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</p>
            <p>Kings hearts are in the hand of the Lord;<note place="margin">Doct.</note> what hee commands, they muſt fulfill.</p>
            <p>The Congregation muſt be aſſembled, the King, Prophets, people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gathered together.<note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliah</hi> proponeth his Text as the foundation for his enſuing words and Actions, which are the words for my Text at this time, <hi>Why halt yee ſo long betweene two opinions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116086:8"/>
               <hi>A word ſpoken in ſeaſon</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 25 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There are times of halting, and here is a Text of halting. <hi>Therefore Text and time agree.</hi> Here you ſee,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A queſtion propounded to the people; <hi>Why halt yee ſo long between two opinions?</hi>
            </p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            <p n="2">2. An anſwer framed for them in a truth ſuppoſed.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            <p>If the Lord be God, follow ye him:<note place="margin">Argum.</note> but the Lord is God, ſhould they have inferred. Therefore we ought to follow him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The obſtupefaction of the people: <hi>They anſwered not a word.</hi>
            </p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
            <p>In the firſt, note
<list>
                  <item>1. The ſpecification of their ſin, <hi>Halting.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The aggravation of it, <hi>Why halt yee ſo long?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The facillity of walking uprightly in the way of Truth.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>They were not twenty ſeducing mizmazing errours (as in theſe Realm-reeling times) but only the rocks of two opinions, the Lord and <hi>Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third wee ſee the wilfull obſtinacy and blindneſſe of the people: <hi>They anſwered him not a word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They had ſome-what in their minds, though they had nothing in their mouths.</p>
            <p>They were convinced by the truth of the Prophet propoſed. But they were unwilling to be converted or reformed, by reaſon of the example of the Princes long cuſtomes thereto by the multitude of the people, and their ſeducings through the numeroſity of <hi>Baals</hi> Prophets, which were 450. and <hi>Eliah</hi> but one againſt them all.</p>
            <p>In the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. part we may read the rule of unerring direction preſcribed, and by all to have beene obſerved. <hi>If the Lord be God, follow yee him: But be alone is God.</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>The firſt is the Checke of Halting.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>is the Cauſe. of Halting.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>is the Cure of Halting.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Or take the diviſion, if you pleaſe, more briefly thus.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Reprehenſion. <hi>Why halt you ſo long betweene two opinions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Caution, Limitation, or Direction. <hi>If the Lord be God, follow him. If</hi> Baall <hi>be God, follow yee him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The non-pluſe obſtupefaction or obduration of the people, who though they were convinced of, yet would not be converted to the truth. <hi>They anſwered him not a word.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Its a great ſin and ſhame to halt between God and <hi>Baal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> truth &amp; error.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are good will ſhow zeale for God;<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> or zeale of <hi>Paſtors</hi> a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116086:9"/>helpe againſt peoples halting. Or downe-right Doctrine muſt throw downe ſin and Idolatry.</p>
            <p>People continue long in a limping condition notwithſtanding long and ſharp reprehenſion, <hi>Why halt ye ſo long.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Many are yet to ſeeke and reſolve which is the true God.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> If <hi>the Lord be God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God alone is to be followed.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Follow him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men are oft convicted,<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> before they are once converted.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome generall Doctrines deduced out of this verſe worthy your ſerious conſideration.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome fruits which fall from the tree of this Text, at the firſt touch thereof. In the handling whereof, Had I either the open utterance of <hi>Paul,</hi> or the eloquent tongue of <hi>Tertullus,</hi> or the well-tuned Cymballs of <hi>David,</hi> or the ſhrill-ſounding bells of <hi>Aaron,</hi> or the ſilver Trumpet of <hi>Hillary,</hi> or the golden mouth of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> or the mellifluous ſpeech of <hi>Origen,</hi> or the thundring voyce of <hi>Perieles,</hi> theſe truths then would both finde and leave you attentive.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall proſecute only the firſt Propoſition ayming to apply it to theſe halting times.<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Its a great ſin and ſhame to halt between God and</hi> Baal, <hi>truth and errour, light and darkeneſſe, the word and the world, Chriſt and</hi> Belial.</p>
            <p>Becauſe there is no communion between theſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. 2 Cor. 6.14.</note> &amp; yet ſuch halters make a communion and union between them; they joyne together what God hath put aſunder; and they put aſunder what God hath in his Word and will joyned together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They call evill good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>and good, evill, they put darkeneſſe for light, and light for darkeneſſe, they put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter.</hi> Now ſuch ſin greatly, becauſe God denounceth woes ſo ſharply againſt them, nay more woes than againſt other grand workers of iniquity, becauſe theſe are wiſe in their owne conceite.<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>21.</hi> Reaſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe theſe halters will be wiſer than God, give Chriſt the lye, ſet the holy Ghoſt to ſchoole.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.24.</note> 
               <hi>No man can ſerve two Maſters, for either be will hate the one, and love the other, or elſe be will hold to the one, and deſpiſe the other. Te cannot ſerve God and Mammon. Yes we can</hi> ſay theſe halters; we can ſerve God in the morning, and the Devill in the afternoone: one Maſter in the Temple, another in the Tavern. We can comply with <hi>Round heads</hi> while we are in their company, and with <hi>Cavalliers</hi> when we are in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; humour and ſooth Papiſts and Puritans, and diſpleaſe neither.</p>
            <p>Becauſe theſe are moſt notorious hypocrices, they think they can be too hard for,<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and deceive both God and Devill: they halt betweene God and Mammon, Chriſt and <hi>Belial,</hi> purity and Popery. They have a tongue for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116086:9"/>the Court cauſe, and a tongue for the Countrey cauſe. God calls for the heart, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. <hi>My ſonne give me thy heart.</hi> Satan will be content with halfe the heart:<note place="margin">2 King. 17.33, 34.</note> God is herein more covetous than the Devill, he will have all or none: the Devill will be contented with halfe, becauſe he knowes if he have any, God will have none. Let ſuch conſider if it be good to ſeeme to be rich, it is better to be ſo; if good, to ſeeme to be good, better to be ſo; if it be bad, to ſeem to be bad, it is worſe to be ſo. Either therefore bee as thou ſeemeſt to be, very good; or ſeem to be as thou art indeed, very bad; If the Lord be God, follow him; if <hi>Baal,</hi> follow him. If thy own private be to be preferred before the publique prefer it, if the publique be to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the private prefer it, elſe profeſſe thy ſelfe to be an hypocrite, more woes are denounced againſt ſuch than againſt any ſinners; eight ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall woes in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13. denounced againſt them.<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place this may ſerve to inform us touching the Cauſe why ſo many faithfull Preachers are ſo zealous that they lift up their voyces like Trumpets; when Trumpets lift up their voyces like Preachers, the glory of God, love of Chriſt, care for the Kingdomes lawes, liberties, conſtraine them. <hi>Obadiah</hi> diſſwades <hi>Eliah,</hi> ver. 10. <hi>Ahab</hi> reproveth him, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. God commanded him, <hi>v.</hi> 1. Whether it be better to obey God or man, judg ye, <hi>Acts,</hi> 4.19. Sin labours to deſtroy the word in the mouths of Miniſters, &amp; Miniſters labour to deſtroy ſin in the hearts of hearers; when fire and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meet there is great ratling and hiſſing. Paint a fire on a piece of cloath, and caſt it into the water, and no noiſe at all, nor contraries, therefore no combate. If miniſters come with painted fire, with ſilken ſayings, flattering words, ſaying <hi>all is well,</hi> no wonder if men halt, limp, trip and fall into the down-fall of damnation,<note place="margin">Zac.</note> feele hell before they feare it: Is it not therefore lawfull, neceſſary, to reſcue mens ſoules as brands out of the fire? <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy heart, but reprove him plainly.</hi> Were not the people here by the zeale of <hi>Eliah</hi> firſt convicted, then converted, crying, <hi>The Lord is God, the Lord is God.</hi> Can it be bad to be zealous in a cauſe that is good, to preſerve a plant from withering, a Beaſt from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a ſheepe from wandring, a houſe from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iring, a ſhip from ſinking, a Citie from ſacking, and Kingdomes from deſtroying, to ſave a ſoule to turne a ſinner from the evill of his wayes? As cold oft breeds an inflamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo the luke-warme devotion of many Paſtors. People have enkindled Gods wrath, and Gods wrath hath blowne up theſe ſad combuſtions wherewith the Land is almoſt conſumed, ſhould not the <hi>Boanerges</hi> labour to take out fire with fire, the fire of Gods wrath by the fire of the Spirit to preſerve from everlaſting burnings?<note place="margin">Jer. 6.29.</note> The lungs and lips of Preachers that are touched with a coale from Gods Altar, are powerfull bellowes to blow up the dying fire of zeale; Is not this Gods worke? and <hi>muſt not they be fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116086:10"/>in Spirit that will ſerve the Lord?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.11. Iſa. 63.15. &amp; 9.7. 2 King. 19.31.</note> whoſe work can never be done while they freeze at it. It is Gods zeale that muſt doe all for us, and muſt not our zeale doe all we can for him? Did Chriſt ſweate, that the Chriſtian ſhould freeze? muſt not all redeemed ones <hi>be zealous of good workes,</hi> Titus 2.14? <hi>Hanniball</hi> by fire made way over the Alpes: ſo muſt Miniſters by zeale over the mountaines of oppoſitions, the tops whereof will not be climbed without great ſtrength, violence, and vivacity.</p>
            <p>Palmes are the Emblemes of victory, but they love to grow in a hot ſoyle. All would have Palms, heate is the meanes for them.</p>
            <p>Fervency in a Chriſtian is the grace of every action; Miniſters muſt perſwade to be zealous, elſe people cannot repent: and they muſt repent, elſe <hi>Chriſt will not come in and ſup with them,</hi> Rev. 3.19. And muſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters perſwade others to be zealous, and ſhall they be dull, cold, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme themſelves? <hi>Wiſedome is juſtified of her children;</hi> the people, place, Text and time call for it. Thus having with the Cock, clapt my wings on my owne breaſt, give me leave to crow unto others alſo; to ſhew men their preſent ſin, to prevent their future ſhame.</p>
            <p>Chriſt lookes on all Newteralliſts as on enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> not as on friends; <hi>Why halt ye ſo long,</hi> ſeeing it is a great ſin and ſhame? Mat. 12.38. <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me: and he that gathers not with me, ſcattereth abroad. Aut mecum totum tene aut totum amitte,</hi> ſaith Greg. <hi>Proditor eſt veritatis, qui aut libere non pronuntiat aut non ſufficienter eam defendant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Traytors are the very off-ſpring of <hi>Judas,</hi> ſhamefully expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſcorne and hatred of all men, both good and bad; It happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to theſe neutralizing middle-men, as to thoſe that dwell in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle roomes of ſome high building; as they are ſmoked and ſmothered by thoſe that dwell under them, and polluted with duſt and filth of thoſe that dwell over them: ſo ſmoake and ſmoother, ſhame &amp; diſgrace are the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch neutrall middle people. They that cleave heartily to neither ſide, are juſtly ſuſpected and abhorred of each ſide; hee that is neither throughly for God nor man, is rejected both of God and man.</p>
            <p>Doe not therefore ſay (in theſe dayes of danger) as ſometimes <hi>Cato</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> did in the Civill Wars betweene <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey. Quem ſugiam video, quem ſequar non video,</hi> I diſcerne whom to flye, but not whom to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.<note place="margin">Mark. 8.34. Judg. 5.23.</note> Chriſt is to be daily followed, or the curſe of <hi>Meroz</hi> to be expected, which words I wiſh (as once <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> did that ſentence, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.11.) were engraven on the doore poſts into which theſe Politicians and Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traliſts doe enter, on the Tables where the ſit, on the diſhes out of which they did eate, on the cups out of which they did drink, on the beds where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they did lye, on the walls of the houſe wherein they did dwell, on the garments which they did were, on the heads of the horſes on which they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116086:10"/>doe ride, on the foreheads of all thoſe whom they doe meete, that they might learne and continually remember, that there is a bitter curſe attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not onely thoſe that powerfully oppoſe Chriſt, but thoſe that neglect to aſſiſt him. But men ſhould doe rather as the noble Souldier (in <hi>Eraſmus</hi>) did to one that told him a moſt numerous Armie was againſt him, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Tanto plus gloriae referemus, quantô ſunt plures, quos ſuperabimus;</hi> The moſt numerous oppoſers make the Chriſtians Conqueſt the more il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious; Chriſts faithfull Souldiers they are all glorious Conquerours,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> they have alwayes Crownes, though ſometimes they are enforced to ſwim to them in ſtreames of bloud: take to thee therefore the heart and courage of <hi>Shammah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23 12.</note> one of <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies, who ſtood and defended the field when all the reſt fled; He that ſtands not by his Maſter in the time of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, is not worthy the name of a ſervant; ſhouldſt thou helpe the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and love them that hate the Lord, therefore is wrath upon thee from before the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2? Such as turne with the Weather-cocke, and field of Corne with every blaſt, will the Lord account as his Servants, Friends, and Souldiers?</p>
            <p>I have read of a Creature which they call a Hedge-hogge or Urchin, which hath two holes, the one towards the North, the other towards the South; if the winde blowes Northwards, it ſtops that hole, and opens the other towards the South, if the winde blowes Southward, it ſtops that hole, and opens the other towards the North; So theſe Neuters, if the one Armie comes to quarter in their Coaſts, they ſtop the mouth of exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them, and open againſt the adverſe Armie; if the other Armie come, they ſtop their mouths in ſpeaking any thing againſt them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen them wide, to rage and raile freely againſt their oppoſites: or I may make the application thus; while the Parliament went on ſmoothly in the beginning under the faire gale of probabilitie, to land the ſhip of intended reformation upon the ſhoare of long deſired and happy ſucceſſe, not a mouth then was open againſt them, but when a Boreas blaſt comes againſt them, an Euroclydontizinge <hi>(i)</hi> a quiet-ſayling-oppoſing-ſtorme, a State ſtaggering, a Realme-reeling tempeſt, under the power of Prerogative Command, then men began to open their mouthes at large, ready to cry downe the very ſame Parliament, by their invectives and imprecations which they had a little, yet long before, cryed up, in their deſires and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayers to God; ſo mutable are theſe diſſembling temporizers, when all things concurre not with their carnall contents and earthly hopes. What will theſe neutralizing double-minded perſons ſay, or how will they anſwer for themſelves, if they live to ſee the warre ended? Shall I gueſſe at their anſwer, and then you may gueſſe at their Ambodexteriſme and palpable hypocriſie? I thinke (when theſe civill or rather uncivill warres
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116086:11"/>are ended) they will anſwer to ſuch as heard them in ſpeeches, and knew them in actions to play faſt and looſe, to be Jacke on both ſides, they will anſwer, I ſay as the Dunſticall Doctor, or equivocating Aſtronomer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; which Story I have read in a Sermon preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, (if my memory fayle not) above forty yeares agoe, which Pedigree of place and time, I name for the more Authorities ſake, that it may not be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to move laughter in the hearers; yet, howſoever the guiltie may laugh at the hearing of it, the innccent may weepe for the laughter of the guiltie: This Aſtronomer in a Moone-ſhine-night walked up and downe the ſtreets in a populous Towne, and looked up unto the Starres, and the people flocking about him, asked him, What weather Maſter Doctor? What weather? Very ſoule, quoth he, very ſoule; and walking along into another ſtreete, and looking into the skie, the people came to him and asked him, What weather, What weather, Sir? To whom he anſwered, Very faire weather, very faire; afterward the weather proving foule, the people that dwelled in the ſecond ſtreete meeting the Aſtronomer, ſaid to him, You were deceived Maſter Doctor, you told us wee ſhould have faire weather, but it proved otherwiſe; To whom he replyed, I did but jeſt in what I ſpake to you, but aske the men that dwell in ſuch a ſtreete, what I ſpake to them, I ſpake in earneſt unto them; So ſuch linſey-wolſey-mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grill-motley-minded-men, being hereafter told, you ſaid ſuch an Armie was in the right, and the other in the wrong, will reply when they ſee the iſſue, I did but jeſt in what I ſpake in ſuch a Cauſe that I ſee now ſunke, but I ſpake in earneſt touching the Cauſe which I now ſee ſtand, and hath prevailed. Like the man mentioned in <hi>Macrobius,</hi> who in the warres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Anthony</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> had two birds or Parrotts; He taught one of them to ſay, <hi>Ave Imperator Antoni,</hi> and the other, <hi>Ave Imperator Auguſte;</hi> ſo that whoſoever got the day, or won the victory, ſtill he had a bird to give him the congratulation of all hayle, or God ſave you Empercur, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhould be <hi>Auguſtus</hi> or <hi>Antonius;</hi> ſo unſiding perſons in theſe ſiding times have a boſome-bird in a readineſſe to ſalute either prevailing partie with a joyfull acclamation of God bleſſe and proſper you, &amp;c. Whereby they become guiltie of the ſinne here reproved, namely, of <hi>balting between two opinions.</hi> The word ſignifies, a lameneſſe on both feete; the ſame word that is tranſlated <hi>halt,</hi> ſignifies lameneſſe on both feete, which is uſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe <hi>Mephiboſheth's</hi> lameneſſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Jacob</hi> had but one ſide lame, therefore there is another word uſed in <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.31. <hi>And as he paſſed over Pennel, the Swnne roſe upon him, and be halted upon his thigh.</hi> Theſe Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts are lame on both feete, they neither ſerve God, King, nor Countrey cordially.<note place="margin">2 King. 17.33, 34.</note> God looks upon divided worſhip as no worſhip: <hi>The Idolaters feared God, and worſhipped Idells;</hi> and in the next verſe it is ſaid, <hi>they feared not God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116086:11"/>Thoſe are threatned ſeverely that ſweared by the Lord and by <hi>Mal chom,</hi> Zeph. 1.5. If the Parliament be not for the weale of the Kingdome' why gaveſt thou a voyce to chooſe them? If they be for the weale of the Kingdome, why doeſt thou not in words, judgement, and practiſe, adhere to them ſtill? Conſider what infamie will befall thee, every one points with the finger, ſaying, There goes an Hypocrite, Shifter, Turne-coat, neither hot nor cold, a traytor to his Countrey; Theſe Apoſtatizers either from Parliament, or from their Countreys good, doe reſemble the Devill, for what makes the Devill ſo black but his Apoſtaſie? What other are ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceders? When the <hi>Lycaonians</hi> ſaw the miracle that <hi>Paul</hi> wrought in curing the Creeple, they cryed out, <hi>The Gods are come downe amongſt us in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men,</hi> Act. 14.10, 11. But when the <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſaw the Viper upon his hand, they eryed out, <hi>This man is a Murtherer, whom vengeance ſuſſers not to live,</hi> Chap. 28.4. When at the beginning of their ſitting, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cured ſuch as were creepled in their Eſtates, and Liberties, when they took away <hi>Ship-money, Monopolies;</hi> When they made the lame to walke, opening priſon doores to ſuch as were in bonds; when they made the dumme to ſpeake, opening the mouthes of many frienced Miniſters, then they could ſay, <hi>Oh this is a bleſſed Parliament;</hi> but when they ſaw Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Flatterers, and Papiſts up in Armes, then men beginne to change their note, and why, O peace, peace, peace upon any termes, yet the Sunne is the Sunne, though ſometimes clouded; Doth not the Lord command,<note place="margin">Zach. 8.16. Verſ. 19. Heb. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Love Peace and Truth,</hi> nay, Truth and Peace; muſt not peace and holineſſe be followed of all? Have not the Parliament petitioned againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for peace; doe not wee pray daily for it? doe not our Armie fight for it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pyrrbus</hi> fought three ſore battles againſt the <hi>Romans:</hi> in the two firſt he got the victorie, but with ſo great loſſe of his men in both, that it was ſaid of him, for the firſt he might <hi>gloriari magis, quàm gaudere,</hi> brag of his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, not rejoyce in it; for the ſecond, he was heard himſelfe to ſay, that if he got ſuch another victorie, he was undone. Conditions of peace (after the firſt victory) were offered by <hi>Cineus Pyrrbus</hi> his Ambaſſadour in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and many among the <hi>Romans</hi> were apt to encline to it, as being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned by <hi>Pyrrbus</hi> his victory. <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> having notice of it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to privacy for a long time, aged and blinde, cauſed himſelfe in his Couch to be carried to the Senate-houſe, and ſaid; Worthy Patriots, I have hitherto with ſore griefe endured loſſe of ſight, but now hearing your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to conclude ſuch a diſhonorable peace with <hi>Pyrrbus,</hi> a proſeſſed enemy to <hi>Rome,</hi> it now troubles me more that I am not deaſe alſo, that my eares might not heate of ſuch an infamy and reproach to ſuch a tenowned Citie of <hi>Rome:</hi> you may make the application.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116086:12"/>But you will ſay,<note place="margin">Queſt. Anſw.</note> who are Neuters?</p>
            <p>Eſt <hi>neutrale Genus, ſignans rem non animatam.</hi> Liſeleſſe men.</p>
            <p>A curſed generation of men who ſeeme not to know their right hand from their left, nor which way to turne. One compares theſe to the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a man; Another to a picture commonly ſeene in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and too often, I beleeve in <hi>England</hi> alſo. In which there is a thing they call a Chriſt on the left hand, another thing they call the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> on the right, and in the middle a third thing called a <hi>Catholicke,</hi> with this inſcription before him, <hi>Cui me vertam, neſcio.</hi> Let us apply it to our times; Chriſt and his truth are on the right hand, (for he hath too long been ſet on the left hand, let us now endeavour to ſet him on the right) the Devill and the Pope on the left hand; the Faith, the Law, Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdome are on the one hand; Popery, ſlavery, prophaneneſſe on the other hand, yet <hi>Cui me vertam neſcio;</hi> he knows not which ſide to take, is not he a Neuter? On the one hand are the great Councell of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who have loſt much outward liberties and profits, to procure peace for the Church, and puritie for Gods worſhip; on the other hand are left<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed men, Robbers, ſpoylers, murderers, roaring Lyons, devouring Wolves, who labour to fight in Popery to the Church, beggary to the State, and ſlavery to the Subject, yet <hi>Cui me vertam neſcio,</hi> to what hand he may turne he cannot tell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſt. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>faſt and pray for us, wee will doe ſo likewiſe,</hi> ſay Gods faithfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their iniſery; Goe feaſt and play, ſwill and ſweare, ſay Athiſticall Papiſts, and popiſhable perſons. God on this day calls for faſting, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill calls to feaſting,<note place="margin">Eſi. 22.12, 13, 14.</note> to riot, ſports, works of calling; God calls to <hi>weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mourning, baldneſſe, girding with ſackcloth; And, Behold,</hi> (and indeed it commands admitation) <hi>joy and gladneſſe, ſlaying Oxen, killing ſheepe, eating fleſh, drinking wine, and ſaying, Let us eate and drinke, for to morrow wee ſhall dye,</hi> if wee'le beleeve Preachers prate, yet <hi>Cui me vertam neſcio,</hi> ſayth your meale-mouth'd-ling-medly-man, your carnall Politician. It was revealed in my eare from the Lord of Hoſts; <hi>Surely this iniquitie ſhall not be purged till yee dye. Ecquis mecum?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 9.32.</note> who is on my ſide who? throw downe this cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Jezabel,</hi> painted pietie, Romiſh Idolatry, Image-worſhip, falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, who will riſe up, with mee againſt the evill doers, who will ſtand for mee againſt the workers of iniquitie? <hi>Pfal.</hi> 94.16. Who will come up to the helpe of the Lord againſt the mighty, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.23? Yet moſt men will ſtand with their hands in their pockets, and their coyne in their Coffers, and will not come forth and ſhew themſelves. I will not undertake to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound a way to reforme them, I thinke I can diſcover ſome cauſe of their encreaſe; pitty, lenity, connivency towards them; pitty ſhewed to enemies, is cruelty to friends; Is it not againſt the law of nature, that they who are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116086:12"/>without naturall affections, ſhould enjoy the common gifts of nature, light, ayre, fire, water? Is it not againſt the law of Nations, Armen, that thoſe Subjects ſhould enjoy the priviledges and immunities of Subjects, who ſee with open face the enemies deſtroying all theſe; yet lay it neither to head nor to heart?</p>
            <p>They that are the ſame, and have done the ſame, for doing whereof o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their neighbour-Neuters have had the skin torne from their fleſh, and their fleſh from their bones, theſe do deſerve to be caſt out of the land. But theſe diſſembling Neuters are the ſame, and doe the ſame which they did in former times that were ſo puniſhed, therefore theſe Compounds de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no favour, but to be caſt out of Citie, Countrey, Kingdome. The Parliament accounts ſuch no better than profeſſed Malignants, (I thinke they are worſe;) true friends to the Parliament ſhould not eſteeme them undangerous enemies to Church, and to the Common-wealth, theſe get to an upper place (if not in ſcituation, yet in ſpeculation) as <hi>Metius Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> did, ſpying which ſide is ſtrongeſt and likelieſt to prevaile, and then towards that ſide they will wheele about and joyne themſelves; But what reward did his carnall compound policy, his divided heart promote him too? My Author ſaith, that the body of <hi>Metius Suffetius</hi> (who ſtood neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the warres between the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Fidenates,</hi> to ſpy which ſide was ſtrongeſt, that thereunto he might turne) was adjudged by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of warre to be tyed to two teemes of horſes, which halled contrary wayee, ſo his body was drawne aſunder, and pluckt into two pieces accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. The portraiture of which Teemes halling, and <hi>Metius Suffetius</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſo drawne aſunder, I wiſh were ſet upon the walls of the houſes, where ſuch Compound Neuters dwell, or on the horſe-heads, on which they doe ride, or on the ſides of the cupsin which they drinke, or on the bedſteads on which they lye, that they might learne by other mens harmes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falling into the like ſinne, for ſeare they fall into the like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>You know the Hiſtory of the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> and <hi>Penuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 8.</note> what <hi>Gideon</hi> deſired of them for his wearied Armies in the purſuite of <hi>Zeba</hi> and <hi>Zalmun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> the <hi>Sucoothites</hi> jeered at him, <hi>You will returne us our bread when you have your enemie in your band.</hi> When will that be? Your enemies are Kings, and Kings will helpe one another; they have power; you are weake, think you to overcome two Kings with your three hundred tyred Souldiers, there is a great peradventure, diſadvantage. Wee will ſee the ſucceſſe firſt cleerer,<note place="margin">Ver. 16.</note> you queſtion not the victory, its a great queſtion to us. <hi>Are the heads,</hi> &amp;c. you know what followes, as <hi>Gideon</hi> threatned to deale, ſo he dealt with them, he tooke the Elders of the Citie, and the thornes and briars of the wilderneſſe, and with them he taught the men of <hi>Succoth;</hi> he taught them?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116086:13"/>a ſore teaching, a fearefull fight to ſee ſo many bloudy bones to ſtart out of the fleſh: a ſharp, but very exemplary for un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iding men in theſe ſiding times; They that will not be taught by precepts, muſt be taught with paine, I wiſh ſuch briars and thornes grew and were ſeene in the hedges that mounded in the grounds of ſuch Compounds, fearefull, faint-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, cowardly, hypocriticall, diſſembling, lukewarme, falſe-hearted, tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous, neutralizing perſons. You know the parable of a man travelling falling among theeves and wounded;<note place="margin">Luke 10.</note> that which was in parable then is in practiſe now, the Land is fallen among theeves, or theeves rather have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len upon the body of the Land; ſhould it not work pitty, compaſſion in all that ſee it? are they <hi>Samaritans</hi> that regard it not? woe, woe to the lookers on, and paſſers by. Curſe yee bitterly ſuch <hi>Merozites,</hi> Judg. 5.23. In cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing curſe, never ceaſe to call for a curſe. <hi>Janius</hi> renders it <hi>Indeſinenter, Curſed be be that doth the worke of the Lord negligently, and that keeps his ſword from bloud,</hi> Jer. 17 3. If negligent workers? What, no workers? that are like ſtanding water, that neither ebs, nor flowes?</p>
            <p>Theſe Ambodexters who are Compounds that care not what ſide pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes, ſhall be rewarded as Neuters, ſhall not have Gods protection; all left-handed perſons ſhall be put on Chriſts left hand, ſhall be ſent away with a <hi>depart from mee;</hi> God comes to helpe all ſimple ones in their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and all ſuch will helpe the Lord in his miſery, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35, 36. <hi>For I was an hungred, and yee gave mee meat: I was thirſtie, and yee gave mee drink: I was a ſtranger, and yee took mee in; naked, and yee clothed mee; I was ſicke, and yee viſited mee; I was in priſon, and yee came unto mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſhewed the ſin, and ſhame of theſe Neuters, I now come to ſhew the Cauſe and Remedy of their Maladie, in the third Uſe;<note place="margin">Uſe <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> which you may call the Solution of the Queſtion, or ſatisfaction of the Doubts, or remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall of the rubs in the way, or which I call (in the Title for theſe times) <hi>the Cauſes and the Cure of halting.</hi> Theſe people ſpake not a word to <hi>Eliahs</hi> Queſtion, yet they murmured in their minds, though they manifeſted it not with their mouthes. But now people both mutter inwardly, and mouth it outwardly, why they halt; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Cauſe.</note> yea, the greateſt part, even of the Parliaments Members, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Parliaments Cauſe: Doe you not thinke they did it out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards the Kings ſide?</p>
            <p>And what thinke you of thoſe few that are turned from the King,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and offered their ſervice to the Parliament againe, confeſſed and recanted their errour, and wondered that they could be ſo farre ſeduced to take up Armes againſt that Parliament which they had taken the Covenant to maintaine? What if many have betrayed their truſt, and deſerted Parliament and Kingdome, doth this juſtiſie their perfidiouſneſſe, and halting condition,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116086:13"/>or condemne the ſincerity of ſuch as goe on uprightly without backſliding? Can any man have any colour to free them from never dying infamie, who made elaborate Orations, faire promiſes, loud proteſtations, <hi>That they would live and dye with the Parliament,</hi> to ſpend their lives and fortunes in the cauſe; confeſſing that <hi>to be the cauſe of God,</hi> &amp; yet either through feare, or hope of favour, have forſaken that Cauſe, (which at firſt they then ſo ſtrangely maintained) and have been inſtruments of betraying much inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, and bringing more cares upon the heads of thoſe that have continued conſtant. If the Kingdome ſtand, doubtleſſe ſuch Traytors ſhall not long ſtand in credit or libertie, but ſhall be brought unto condigne puniſhment, that others may feare Apoſtacy, and the ſincere be cheriſhed in their fidelity. If the Kingdome doe not ſtand (for a houſe, a Citie, a Kingdome divided cannot long ſtand) God will finde them out and reach them a rap; for curſed be he that putieth his <hi>hand to the Plough, and looketh backs, is not fit for the Kingd me of Heaven.</hi> How can it be expected other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but that Gods curſe and ſhame with men, ſhould overtake ſuch run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awayes, and all other diſſembling Neuters, who ſeeme to be ſo high in eminency above others, yet have diſcovered ſuch baſe ſpirits, when as the loweſt peaſant would hardly be perſwaded to doe more monſtruouſly, nay, ſcarce Heathens would have been hyred to doe ſo much: Let ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers <hi>never account hypocriſie a ſinne, or ſinceritie a grace, nor Chriſtianitie an honour unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What doe they diſcover themſelves to be in the hearts of all that know them, but baſe peaſantly ſpirited ſpectacles of diſgrace and infamie, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying their own certain proprieties, liberties, (in hope of uncertain ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and profits in the Clouds,) yea, captivating and ſlaying their owns poſteritie and children, together with the Inhabitants of a whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? If the Members departed be the greater number than thoſe that ſtood ſound, why did not thoſe continue in the Houſe to have overvoted the reſt, and ſo have carried on their deſigne with more eaſe and ſafetie, with leſſe charge, danger, diſcredite, to themſelves, their fortunes, and their poſteritie, which now they are lyable to undergoe? Howſoever, many ſimpletones in the Countrey may be perſwaded and deluded that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of themſelves are departed to the Kings ſide; it is a groſſe untruth, for it is reported for truth, that about (ſome ſay at leaſt) 248. are in or of the Commons-Houſe, and I hope the flight of the perfidious, gives not diſanullity to the reſt?</p>
            <p>But let the number be few or many, the Cauſe is one and the ſame ſtill as at the firſt, and their Call lawfull, and if many more ſhould betray their truſt, is not the Kingdome, the people bound with perſon and purſe to preſerve the reſt that labour to preſerve their Religion, Lawes, Libertles, for themſelves, and their poſteritie?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116086:14"/>The fewer they be that have ſtood permanent when ſo many have been Traytors, it is ſo much the more honourable to the former, as it is vitupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and diſhonourable to the latter.</p>
            <p>Hadſt thou not a vote in chooſing them particularly? If ſo, why ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not thou have a heart and a hand to defend them in the generall, which conſiſted of ſo many particulars? <hi>Why balteſt thou ſo long? Why trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt thou at the ſtone of offence?</hi> Which may ſo eaſily be removed, if thou wouldeſt but caſt thy eye of Reaſon to conſider thereon.</p>
            <p>The examples of other great ones ſo increaſing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Cau.</note> adhering to the King in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Shall Chriſt be ſet upon the footſtoole, becauſe great ones will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure him on the throe?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Pſal. 2.</note> Doe not the Scripture tell us, that <hi>Kings of the earth ſtand up, and Princes conſult together againſt the Lord, and his anoynted, ſaying, Let us breake their bonds, and caſt their cords away from us.</hi> Why doe the Heathen rage when God will continue his Sonne upon his holy hill? You know it is a truth, <hi>Greatneſſe is ſeldome accompanied with Goodneſſe: Not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26. Pſal. Col. 3.</note> Their bellies are filled with the hid treaſure of the earth, therefore they ſeldome have appetite to hunger and thirſt after that life which is hid with Chriſt in God. They ſo minde Belly-bleſſings, as that they neglect the care of ſpirituall mercies. Yet a Pearle is a Pearle, is precious, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with the Cocke preſerre the Barley-Corne before it. Greatneſſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with goodneſſe, is like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver, (as <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior eſt virtus veniens e corpore pulcro:</hi>) Pietie in Majeſtie is moſt eminent, tranſient,<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.2.</note> and communicative; it is like <hi>Aarons</hi> oyle that deſcended from the head to the Beard, and ſo to the skirts of the clothing; the Family, the Pariſh, the Countrey ſhall ſmell more fragrantly, be animated more cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, hold out the more conſtantly by the good examples of the mightie. As <hi>Labans</hi> flocks increaſed the better for <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſake, and <hi>Potiphars</hi> affaires ſucceedeth the more proſperous for <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſake.<note place="margin">Act. 27.</note> And <hi>Pauls</hi> fellow-paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſped the better, were landed more ſafely for his ſake: ſo meane ones, Tenants, children, families, thrive and grow the better, are more good and conſtant by reaſon of the goodneſſe and conſtancy of their Superiours. They being as a great Oake, which ſtanding yeeldeth ſhelter and ſafety to them that ſtand under it; but falling cruſheth down the underwood neere unto it. They being as freſh-fiſh, which if it be ſweet in the head, thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt taſte of the whole body, but if the head ſtinke, the reſt of the body is tanted; if the fountaine be polluted, can the channell be cleane?</p>
            <p>Are not great ones, Landlords, Gentlemen, as fountaines, as heads, as Oakes: they being for the greateſt part ſo corrupt, rotten, vile, is it any wonder their Tenants, neighbours, underlings, dance after their pipe?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116086:14"/>
               <hi>Jeremy</hi> went to the people to expect information, but found it not, they were ſimple ones, unlettered ones, had not ſo much leiſure, bookes, abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, opportunities: he went therefore to the great ones, looking for better things from them, <hi>but theſe altogether broke the yoke, burſt the bonds.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.5.</note> He could not expect the common ſort to be good, when the great ones were ſo bad. <hi>Doe any of the great ones, the chiefe Prieſts and Phariſees beleeve on him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.48.</note> How dare you move one way, when men of high place looke another way?</p>
            <p>As I reade of ſome Maſter or Captaine, that becauſe be was crook back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all the reſt of the Schollars or Souldiers ſtooped; as the flattering ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſaid, <hi>Ait? aio; negas? nego.</hi> Doth my Maſter ſay thus? ſo doe I alſo; doth he deny it? ſo doe I alſo. The coward ze of the Gentry have been a great bane to the Countrey, becauſe <hi>exemplum praevalet in re qualibet,</hi> they have been content to make Kings to be Gods, that they themſelves might be Kings. But conſider how God hath infatuated their Couſells, and defeated their hopes, <hi>Parturiunt montes naſcetur ridiculus mus.</hi> They conceive a miſchiefe, and brought forth a lye. They have expoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſtorme and contempt of all good men, becauſe they permit their greatneſſe to bid adiew to goodneſſe. They caught after the ſhaddow, and ſo have loſt the ſubſtance too; and they have but the bones of <hi>Prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi> left, for them, the fleſh being devoured. Sumble not therefore at thoſe bones, have not their perſons in admiration, take not their evill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for imitation, ſeeing <hi>great ones are ſeldome good ones.</hi> Many future gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſhall call them curſed, becauſe they came not forth to the helpe of the Lord againſt the mightie; they had not a foote to ſtand up in the gap,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.30.</note> they had not a hand to make up the hedge for the Land, that the Lord might not deſtoy it; <hi>mightie ones ſhall be mightily tormented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe they ſiune againſt many meahes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Can.</note> enjoyed more by them than by other men.</p>
            <p>Becauſe they cauſe many to fall through their default:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Can.</note> which if people did beleeve, they might be preſerved <hi>from balting between two opionions.</hi> Let people therefore for their preſervation againſt the danger of this ſtone of offence, pray often to the Lord, that <hi>he would make great ones to be good, and good ones to be great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miſpriſſion or overprizing of Prerogative, hath blinded the eyes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3</hi> Can.</note> and cripled the feete of many a man: the Parliament, the people, the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (ſay many) oppoſe the Kings Prerogative, this makes many halt and ſtagger.</p>
            <p>The honour of a King conſiſteth in the multitude of people.<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>Prov.</hi>
               </note> Thoſe that labour moſt to diminiſh people, doe moſt diſhonour a Prince. If the Kings of this Land have not a power to contradict the Cenſure and Judgements of inſertions Courts, ſhould they have power to contradict the ſupreame
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116086:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116086:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116086:16"/>Courts or Judicature? 'Tis true, the Lawes of the Kingdome are called the Kings Lawes; not that either he made them, or can at his pleaſure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, but that he is or ought to be the <hi>Conſervator of them as well as the Conſenter to eſtabliſh them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true,<note place="margin">Hen. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> a King of this Land wrote to the Parliament, ſaying, <hi>Nollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Praerogativam noſtram diſputari,</hi> but they anſwered his <hi>nollumus</hi> with a <hi>nollumus; Nollumus Leges Angliae mutari.</hi> Is it not juſt that Princes ſhould be ruled by Lawes? otherwiſe their will would be a Law, and ſo inſtead of Statutes, there would be an Arbitrary, a Tyrannicall power, which might increaſe to infinite, to monſtrous ſhapes, that either ignorance, impietie, luſt, or ambltion of Princes ſhould bring forth. If all Law and power lay in their own breaſts, a Kingdome could never promiſe themſelves ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, longer than a pious and prudent Prince reigneth: But as the King changeth, the Lawes and Governments of the Kingdome muſt alter: And he that out-lives (as it may happen) two or thres Kings, ſhall <hi>not know what is the Law of the Land, or what to call his owne.</hi> Becauſe he muſt not be beholding to Law, but to the will of the King for what are his rights and proprieties.</p>
            <p>By whoſe ſole permiſſion he may ſay, <hi>This is mine.</hi> When Lawes and Law-makers are ſuppreſſed, are not the Subjects (for whoſe ſake they are made) oppreſſed? When the former looſe their power and priviledge, the other looſe their due and propriety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the bead is ordained for the good of the members, and not the members for the good of the head; ſo a Chriſtian King is ordained for the good of the people, and not the people for the good of the King;</hi> i. principally. I am the head, you are the members; I am the Shepheard, you are the ſheepe; I am the husband, you are the wife. And will any man think me a Chriſtian King to be a Poliganiſt; ſaid King <hi>James</hi> in his ſpeech to the Parliament <hi>March</hi> 19. 1603?</p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> wrote to <hi>Eraſmus</hi> to reſolve him what he thought concerning the writings of <hi>Luther? Eraſmus</hi> returned anſwer in writing, that <hi>many things in the Writings of Luther were condemned as wicked and hereticall, which in the writings of Bernard and Auſtine are accounted as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſound;</hi> ſo many things were of eſteeme as good and commendable in the dayes of King <hi>James,</hi> which are condemned as wicked and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the time of King <hi>Charles.</hi> As though the over-prizing of Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, ſhould pull downe all authoritie of Lawes, or Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I will neither profeſſe ſo much ignorance or arrogance, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a way, as to delineate the diſproportion, to compoſe the differences touching Princes Prerogatives, and Parliaments Priviledges: I know this point hath been pulpited and in print Preſſed by farre more able heads and hands than my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116086:16"/>If Kings may doe whatſoever they pleaſe, what need then of any Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? If there be no neceſſity of Parliament, what need the troubles of Subjects to chooſe Knights and Burgeſſes, or they called, to ſit being cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen? If there be a neceſſitie of Parliament, why ſhould they not be conſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with? If conſulted with, why ſhould not their Counſell be embraced? The Counſell of <hi>Baſyll</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, decreed that as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of a generall Councell, is above the Pope; ſo the Authoritie of a generall Aſſembly of a Kingdome, is above the King, which is to be ſubject to Lawes. All ſuch are to be eſteemed, as flatterers, who attribute ſuch large authoritie unto Kings, as that they will not have them bound under any Lawes: ſuch talke otherwiſe than they thinke. Chriſt himſelfe (ſaith <hi>Jewell</hi> in his Apologie) at the beginning was univerſally received and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured through this Realme by aſſent of Parliament, and without aſſent of Parliament, the Pope himſelfe was never received, no not in the late time of Queene <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dion</hi> praiſed <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour, becauſe when he ſet a Tribune over the <hi>Praetors,</hi> and put a ſword into his hand, he ſaid; <hi>Hoe pro me utere ſi ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta imperavero, ſi injuſta, contra me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt know, <hi>Plus vident oculi, quam oeulus,</hi> a few private ſpirits, may not be conceived to diſcerne more than the choiceſt wits, moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pious judgements in the whole Nation, who have been brought and kept together (in the middeſt of all difficulties and dangers) by Gods wonderfull providence, and by the earneſt prayers of many thouſands of people in the three Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Parliaments may erre, and I thinke this doth, if they doe not redreſſe injuries preſented, and performe the Declarations printed, and promiſed to be confirmed; and may not one man, one King, much more erre? Doth not <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay, <hi>Take away the droſſe from the ſilver,<note place="margin">Pro. 25.4.</note> and a veſſell of uſe ſhall be to the finer?</hi> Is not the King the ſilver, the wicked Counſell as droſſe? Doe not the next words make the Reddition, <hi>Take away the wicked from before the King, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſſe?</hi> Wilt thou be preſerved from this ſtumbling ſtone, this cauſe of halting, conſider what he ſaid, that was a halting perſon, and after profeſſed and promiſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, &amp;c. Sir <hi>Edward Deering?</hi> I ſaid, quoth he, whileſt I was at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> I did beleeve the King might ſafely goe to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> with forty men. I then ſaid ſo, and I thinke it will not be well till the King doth ſo. Oh, that God would raiſe up unto his ſight ſome upright ones, that from halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons (that have ſeduced him) they may become perſwaders of him to returne in perſon and affection to his great Counſell.</p>
            <p>The greateſt part of the people, adhering rather to the Court,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Cauſe.</note> than Kingdomes Cauſe, make men halt, in head, hand, and heart, doubting whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116086:17"/>it be better to goe forward, or ſit ſtill in the Common Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The moſt men ever ſide with the ſtrongeſt ſide,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Exod 23. Rom. 12.</note> be it right or wrong. But thou muſt not follow <hi>a multitude to doe evill. Faſhion not your ſelves like to this world. For the world lieth in wickedneſſe,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>John,</hi> and wouldeſt thou deſies to follow after wickedneſſe? Whereas the Scripture commands; <hi>Eſchew the which is evill, and follow after that which is good. Broad is the way leading to deſtruction, and many follow that way.</hi> Is it not better to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the few to ſalvation, than the many to deſtruction? The one is of large latitude, therefore many travell in it, the other ſtraight, therefore few delight to finde it. Men, like old ſheepe are apt to be ſeduced. The world divided into thirty parts (as is obſerved) nineteene of thirty are ſtill overgrowne with Heatheuiſh Idolatry; of the other eleven, ſix over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with Mahumetiſme; then but five of thirty remaine for Chriſtians, and among them, how many are ſeduced Papiſts, Sectaries of all ſorts, prophane irreligious ones, and how few Proteſtants iudeed? who if they <hi>have a ſhew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5</note> 
               <hi>yet deny the power of godlineſſe.</hi> Of the foure ſorts of Seeds, one part onely fell on good ground. Looke into moſt Cities, Townes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, Families; little thereof lookes like good ground, encloſed, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nured, and planted, to bring forth, <hi>cultu, fructu, ornatu,</hi> unto good; but like a common waſte, over growne with weeds of ſinne, and ſo are endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered to looſe their God, ſouſes, hope, happineſſe.</p>
            <p>It is true, <hi>the more the merrier,</hi> if in a good matter, in a right way, for then <hi>Bonum quo communius ed melius,</hi> ſo <hi>malum quô communius, eo pejus.</hi> Wilt thou be therefore as the Weather-Cocke, to be carried away with every winde, whether of Doctrine. Diſcipline, or Doings? Doe not you know, <hi>Quat homines, tot ſententiae;</hi> ſo many men, ſo many opinions. Doe not you know, <hi>Vulgus belluae eſt multorum capitum?</hi> Did not the people cry one while <hi>Hoſanna;</hi> another while <hi>Crucifie?</hi> Would they not have done ſacrifices unto <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> crying, <hi>Gods are come downe unto us in the likeneſſe of men?</hi> Another while eſteemed them as Bablers and pullers down of the goddeſſe <hi>Dinna.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 28.4.</note> Did not they erre while they ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer,</hi> while the Viper was on his hand, and while he ſhakt it off? Did they not ſuddenly change their mindes (as ſudden as he caſt off the Viper) and eſteemed him as a God?<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> The Field of Corne boweth it ſelfe as the winde driveth it, ſo moſt men turne and winde themſelves as the Times are, and faſhions goe, fit their ſavles for every winde, are Papiſts with Papiſts, Roundheads with Roundneads, and Royaliſts with the Royaliſts; they will ſide with the ſtrongeſt ſide, be it right or wrong. All their Religion is taught by the Precepts of men; they will beleeve men againſt the Lord, when they will not bete eye the Lord againſt men. When as men common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are led by ſenſe, rather than by reaſon, by reaſon than by faith, yet the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116086:17"/>naturall man perceiveth not the things that are of God, neither can he. For blinde men cannot judge of colours, nor deafe men of ſounds, the multitude uſually call evill good, and good evill, bitter ſweet,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.20.</note> and ſweet bitter: but woe be to ſuch as ſet a wrong eſtimation upon right objects. And woe to all ſuch as follow ſuch blinde Guides, that draw others with themſelves into the ditch of Damnation. One in the right is more ſafely to be followed, than many in the wrong. When <hi>Apollo</hi> by Oracle at <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos</hi> told the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that one man diſagreed, though all the reſt of the Citie aſſented; And they were much troubled, to know who that was: <hi>Phocion</hi> his own accord ſtept forth and ſaid, Give over to wonder and inquire who that man is? <hi>I am he of whom the Queſtion is,</hi> for indeed I like of nothing that you goe about. And have not good people a better and greater matter to ſtand for (though ſingular) than <hi>Phocion</hi> had? Chriſt allowed ſingularitie, ſaying, <hi>What ſingular thing doe you? Peter</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.47. 1 Pet. 4.4.</note> where he blames all ſuch as thinke it ſtrange, that others did not run with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot.</p>
            <p>The great preſſures by payments,<note place="margin">Cauſe <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> makes men halt and weary of the Cauſe. If payments might ceaſe, and Trade goe on, many would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with any condition for matter of Religion. The exhauſted expences makes people deeme ill of the inſtruments of Reformation. They had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lawes, Liberties, Religion, and all were loſt, than to be at any coſt for their preſervation. With the <hi>Gadarens,</hi> they will part with a Saviour, rather than with their ſwine. Now conſider who are the cauſe of expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thoſe that labour to maintaine their rights, or thoſe that endeavour to deſtroy them? Can Papiſts, Delinquents, Traytors, Malignants, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowell themſelves of all their treaſure, to raiſe up and maintaine an Armie againſt the Counſell of the Kingdome (which are the life of the whole Land) and ſhall the Inhabitants that profeſſe themſelves Proteſtants, and free Deniſons, grumble to part with a part, that they may preſerve the whole? Is it not juſt that God ſhould ſuffer ſuch halting Wretches to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh together with their money, and to give over their poſteritie to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bondage, who will not expoſe their perſons and purſes to ſtand up in the Gap, againſt deſtroying enemies? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30.</p>
            <p>Is it not better ſmart once, than ake for ever? to endure a little lancing of the fleſh, to make way for a ſound Cure; to be at charge with a Surgeon and Phyſician, than to want limbes and life? And ſhould our Coyne ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be preſerved, than our Countrey, our perſons, our purſes, rather than our poſteritie, rather than a Nation, the whole Church of God, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the everlaſting wellfare of the ſoule is concerned? Doe not our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries lay all at ſtake, both purſe, policy, power, yea, life, neck, and all, rather then the Catholique Cauſe ſhould come to confuſion,<note place="margin">Luke 10.8.</note> and ſo are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116086:18"/>wiſer in their generation, than the children of light? Wherefore, O Man, conſider that now thy own eſtate, life, libertie, thy neighbour, thy poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, thy native Countrey,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> thy God, thy Chriſt, call for thy aſſiſtance, whether in perſon or purſe, <hi>to helpe the Lord againſt the mightie.</hi> Wilt thou then ſuffer all theſe to fall to the ground through thy default? If Papiſts, Projectors, Malignants, Atheiſts, ſhould prevaile, may not wee ſay, Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well Law, Libertie, Eſtate, Proprietie, Religion, Parliament, and Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? And ſhall any (but miſerable Miſcreants) more grudge paines and charge to preſerve, than they doe to deſtroy all?</p>
            <p>If O Man, thou murmure herein at Payments and Taxations, then thou loveſt thy money more than thy Maker, thy ſilver better than thy ſelfe, thy Gold before thy God, thy profit more than the preſervation of thy ſelfe and poſteritie, thy coyne more than thy Conſcience, thy own luſts before the Law of the Kingdome; thy carnall reaſon, before true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Conſider but the preſſure they are ſubject to, where the Anti-Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Army comes, and continues; <hi>All</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is the Kings, and wee are for the King;</hi> it is a great mercy, they thinke, if they eſcape with their lives; the little finger of the one, is heavier than the whole loynes of the other. The husbandman adventureth great expence in ſeed-time, in hope of an harveſt;<note place="margin">Prov. 3.9.</note> now is our ſeed time for the preſervation of a Land, for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion, therefore honour God with thy ſubſtance; let not this conceit hatched in thy head, cauſe thee to halt in thy heart; but remember, <hi>Thoſe that honour the Lord, he will honour,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30.</p>
            <p>Feare of Plundering, makes many ſtagger in reſpect of part-taking with either:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Cauſe.</note> If they reveale themſelves, they are made a prey to the will of the adverſaries, therefore ſo they may ſleepe in a whole skin, they dread not the danger of a tattered Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Yet when theſe unſiding ones have uſed all their power and policy to eſcape;<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> the enemy have oft-times come and been as cruell to them as to the moſt upright. Many that for feare have been moſt unhelpfull and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to their Countrey, have felt the hand of their conceited friends as heavy upon them as upon their neighbours eſtate; and their hypocriſie could not be a ſufficient protection to them. But why ſhouldeſt thou feare Plundering, and ſo make the feare more than the hurt? They who have been Plundered, their feare is already paſt; and thou makeſt thy ſelfe by thy tormenting feare all thy life long ſubject to this fiend, as if death were approached, the King of feare? Doeſt thou not know, that either thou muſt be plundered from the world, or the world from thee? Art thou now being deprived of eſtate, friends, libertie, in any other eſtate, than thou waſt in, when thou cameſt into the world? or ſhalt be, when thou goeſt out of the world? If thou couldeſt but plunder thy ſelfe in thy contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116086:18"/>before others doe in action, it would not be ſo grievous unto thee: As <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> being told of the death of his Sonne, I am not much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled therewith, ſaid he, becauſe I long confidered before,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> 
               <hi>that he was but mortall.</hi> Did not our Saviour foretell, that heere thieves ſhould breake through and ſteale, and cautioned us thereby to lay up Treaſure there where thieves could not breake through and ſteale? <hi>Vileſcunt temporaria, dum recordantur aeterna.</hi> The loſſe of under-Moone contents, Creature-Comforts, cannot diſturbe, when the preſence of ſpirituall mercies doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect us; Had not many been miſerable for ever, if they had not been miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable once? Their preſent belly-bleſſings had prevented the comfort of their inſuing eternall Glory. The Arch Plunderer the Devill (under whom others are but inſtruments) might have ſnatched away their ſoules at their deaths, and where had they then been? <hi>O foole, this night will they fetch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy ſoule, and where then ſhall theſe things be?</hi> Thy Executors then had not been more nimble to have carried thy body to the grave, than this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Plunderer would have been (like a nimble under-Sheriffe) quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ready to take all into execution, and carry thy ſoule into Hell: Feare not therefore though they have or can hurt the body, <hi>and can doe no more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> (intimating that they would hurt the ſoule alſo, if they could.) It is true, the outward condition of plundered perſons, deprived of ſome libertie, wealth, wife, children, comforts, hath had a ſad aſpect to looke upon by the eye of reaſon. But conſider (deare Chriſtians) are you driven from the Creature, to the Creator, what if forced from the lower, yet haſted to the upper ſprings, from the ſtreame to the fountaine, from worldly, to heavenly Enjoyments; Whether the loſſe in the one be greater than the gaine in the other?</p>
            <p>Before theſe troubles you had Ordinances common with other belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, but now your daily food, is choiceſt morſells, waters of life, ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive refections, <hi>Benjamins</hi> Meſſe, the love of God, the power of Chriſt, the Spirit of Glory, the care of Angels, the prayers of Saints, are all upon the wing for your preſent welfare, your Earth is diſſolved before your body; your Heaven prevents you before your time, your joyes are immediate, you reape without ſowing, you feed on the kernell, and breake not the ſhell, you reſt from your labours in this life; the bloud of Chriſt, the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, the joy of the Spirit, the food of Angels,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> the many great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding precious promiſes, whereby you are made partakers of the divine nature: are not theſe the daily repaſts of your ſoules? Such honour have all Gods Saints, they have Heaven whilſt they are here on Earth: and can they then be in a miſerable, diſtreſſed condition? Such are to be looked upon, I doe not know, whether with more compaſſion, or holy emulation, to whom it is given, not only to beleeve, but to ſuffer for the ſake of Chriſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116086:19"/>
               <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.29. Whether the depth of miſery, or the weight of Glory by greater in theſe, is hard to diſtinguiſh; halt not therefore at this ſtone.</p>
            <p>Selfe-ſeeking,<note place="margin">Gau. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> with the neglect of the Publique, makes men goe in a lazie or limping pace, when men ſo looke to things at home, for their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ends, as that they neglect the Publique: If mens eyes be ſeriouſly fixed on their own pleaſure, or profit, their hearts cannot be guided by a right rule. When our Saviour propounded the Parable of the husbandmen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Scribes and Phariſees, ſaying <hi>What ſhall be done to theſe husbandmen?</hi> The <hi>Jewes</hi> anſwered,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.41. Luk. 20.16.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall miſerably deſtroy theſe husbandmen,</hi> Yet in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpel, where our Saviour ſaid, <hi>He ſhould miſerably deſtroy them,</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> anſwered, <hi>God forbid.</hi> In one Goſpel their anſwer is related to be, <hi>He ſhall miſerably deſtroy them:</hi> in the other Goſpel, the Anſwer is related to be on the contrary, <hi>God forbid.</hi> How can theſe agree? Yes, (ſaith <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi>) for firſt they ſay, <hi>He will miſerably deſtroy theſe but handmen;</hi> But when they perceived Chriſt aymed at them, then they ſaid, <hi>God forbid:</hi> ſo helpfull to halting for owne ends, and ſelfe-indangering-reſpects.</p>
            <p>Many ſeerned forward for the Parliament at the beginning before the wars were raited, but when they ſaw the King oppoſe the Parliament, then they fall off likewiſe, (like Beaſts that cropt the Thees that gave them ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) being <hi>reſolved to account Kings to be Gods, that they themſelves may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Kings.</hi> But truth ſtandeth in the open field, knowes neither father nor mother, houſe nor home, Land nor Lordſhip, all goe down, to Church and Common-wealth may ſtand, Chriſt and his Goſpel may be ſet up.</p>
            <p>But is it not reaſon every man ſhould looke to himſelfe?</p>
            <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Object. Sol. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> is it not greater reaſon every man ſhould looke to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, wherein every good mans private doth conſiſt? Pray <hi>for the Peace of the Citie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 29.7.</note> ſaid the Prophet to the captived oner, <hi>Knoweſt thou not that in the Peace thereof thou ſhalt have Peace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What place ſhould be left for reaſoning about reaſon, when faith ſhould have the predominance:<note place="margin">Sol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Da mihi baptizatam rationem;</hi> Mortified reaſon, ſaith one, this is your victory that overcometh the world, (and all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſoning) even your faith.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.4.</note> Naturall reaſon may be a drawer of water for the Officers uſe, but it muſt not have office of Command in Gods Church and Common-wealths buſineſſe; every man knoweth that the Saints in Heaven are the leaſt propriaries to their own will. Chriſt himſelfe ſaid; <hi>I am not come to doe mine own will, but the will of him that ſent mee:</hi> which, were it but remembred, it would be a meanes that many from halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, might be preſerved. In good works doing, men muſt not ayme at themſelves, much leſſe in evill actions attempt to ſeeke their own riſing by others ruine. When the whole State ſtaggers, and the Realme reelds, muſt they continue in a lazie, lame, halting eſtate and poſture, with their hands
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116086:19"/>in their pockets, moneys in their Coffers, and tongues in their mouthes, without bringing them forth for the preſervation of the Publique, <hi>viz.</hi> Kingdome, Religion, Law, Libertie, and Poſteritie? I ſaid in actions good and commendable, they muſt not ayme at their own ends. The man that was in the Boate where the Kings Crowne was, and the Crowne occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally falling into the water, he leaping after it and recovering it to ſave himſelfe and it, putting the Crowne upon his own head, that ſo he might ſwimme the better to the Boate or Shoare; though he was thanked for his adventure, yet was he blamed for his boldneſſe in putting the Crowne up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own head. Chriſts Crowne is now fallen (as it were into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) and is in danger of ſinking, labour to preſerve it, but not for thy own praiſe or profit ſake, much leſſe muſt his Crowne be ſet upon the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, and Kings Crowne, yea private mens reaſons and reſpects ſet upon the Throne. The 24. Elders (<hi>Revel.</hi> 4.) threw downe their Crownes at the foote of Chriſt, the King of Kings. You know, <hi>Vriah, Nehemiah,</hi> and others, denied their own comforts, and contentments, Court-favours, company of wife, yea, to change their own Cloaths for the Publique ſake. It is an undeniable truth, he that will lift up one that is fallen, muſt ſtoope himſelfe; He that loves father or mother more than Chriſt, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Chriſt. Chriſt ſtill called his Mother <hi>Woman,</hi> (as one obſerves) <hi>Woman what have I to doe with thee?</hi> Woman, not Mother, to ſhew, that in matters of Religion, wee are to know no relations. Were this beleeved and obſerved, the warres by Gods mercy quickly might be ended: thinke on it, and thou wilt halt no longer between thy private ſeeming, and the publique certain good.</p>
            <p>The eighth Cauſe of Halting, is undeſire of change, for doubt of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tumults, or of changing for the worſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> Cauſe.</note> The wicked feare and flie when no man purſueth, but the righteous is bold as a Lyon. The feare for the preſent, touching what will be for the future, is moe than the hurt it ſelfe that ſhall be. Many will be content to abide in darkneſſe and ſlaviſh conditions, for feare of ſhadowes they may meet with, in an altered eſtate; Like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> puniſhed a little with want towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> they wiſhed themſelves in <hi>Aegypt</hi> againe, to enjoy their Leeks and Onions inſtead of their Manna, Angels food. Men are now on their march towards ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and will they deſire to returne unto <hi>Aegypt</hi> againe? It is then juſt that they ſhould never enter into Gods reſt. Will not men endure change of Maſters, and change of ſervants, ſo it be for their profit; change of horſes, change of dogges, ſo it further their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? change of aire, change of dyet, ſo it tends to their health? May men deſire, new Maſters, new ſervants, new Miniſters, new Magiſtrates, change of apparell, dyet, houſes, and ſhall they onely dreame of danger, in new
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116086:20"/>reformation, in change of manners? The Apoſtle commands, <hi>Faſhion not your ſelves like to this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>but be you changed</hi> (inwardly in minde, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in manners) elſe you cannot prove, or approve, what is the <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table will of God,</hi> or what is the <hi>reaſonable ſervice</hi> required in man towards God, who is a Spirit, and muſt be worſhipped in Spirit and in truth. Are thoſe obſtinate <hi>Jewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 44.</note> thinke you, to be followed, who ſaid, <hi>The Word that thou haſt ſpoken unto us wee will not heare, but will doe whatſoever is good in our own eyes;</hi> for then wee had peace and plenty of all things, but ſince wee leſt off to worſhip the Queene of Heaven, wee have had troubles, warres, dearth, and ſcarcitie of all things. Many deſired our little great-<hi>Will</hi> (I meane Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi>) to be changed and taken out of the way, and will they deſire many great little <hi>Wills</hi> to be Hierarched, and ſet up in the place thereof; ſuch a change may be from bad to worſe.</p>
            <p>You have heard of the old Woman, I beleeve when all other people prayed for the removall of a Tyrannicall Prince; ſhee onely prayed for his continuation; being asked the reaſon thereof, why ſhee prayed for his continuing, when all others prayed for his removall; Shee replyed, ſuch a Prince was bad, and people deſired his exchange, and the next was worſe, and the next worſe than he, and this worſe than that; and if this be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, quoth ſhee, I thinke the next will be the Devill himſelfe. So prone na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally are people to imagine, that all changes ſhall be for the worſe. Men know not what may be in, and after, therefore deſire an abode in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition. Which have occaſioned many mens halting, ſtumbling, falling, which might have been preventable by a change. Is it not better to change from bad to good, than from bad to worſe? Seeing every man by every action ſteps neerer to Heaven, or to Hell. I beleeve one of the Cauſes of ſo many ſad changes in our outward condition, hath been new fangled conceits touching changeableneſſe in Religion. <hi>For when they choſe new Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>then warre was in the Gates.</hi> Therefore a change from new Gods to the true God, will procure peace in our gates. Can it be imagined any danger to have unprofitable Trees, dregges of Popery, which God did never plant, to be removed out of his Orchard, and his own Plants to be ſet in the place thereof? What hurt hath been by the change of Monkes and Fryers, Abbots and Pryors, Hermits and Nunnes? Shall their perſons be removed, and their profeſſion be retained? If there hath been no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of repentance in the Land for caſting out thoſe Locuſter, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſhould be feared by inacting new reformation, and aboliſhing old Traditions?</p>
            <p>Aske all the Reformed Churches, whether ever they grieved, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daily rejoyced, to have their Religion of Idolatry and Superſtition to be baniſhed out of their Coaſts? I know the thoughts of the change of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116086:20"/>Epiſcopacy, is a great trouble, and a cauſe of halting to many men; but let them remember the high Commiſſion, &amp; Biſhops Courts, in Counties, and the ſtrange monſtrous Concomitances attending the ſame, they will ſcarce deſire or plead for the reintertainment of them againe. It cannot be denied but that Epiſcopacy hath been a great ſupporter of Papacie; where the one falls, the other cannot long ſtand. Pluck up but this one weed in the Antichriſtian Kingdomes over Sea; let Biſhops onely be removed from <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine, Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as they are likely to be from <hi>Britaine,</hi> the Pope can no more ſtand there hereafter, than a head can without his body. The Maxime was falſe, No Biſhop no King; but its certain, No Biſhop no Pope. The Bulles from <hi>Rome,</hi> bred ſo many Calves in <hi>Britaine,</hi> that there was a neceſſitie of Ceſſation, or ſacrifice of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods wrath can be expected to be pacified toward the Nation. Was not a Reformation deſired long in the Land by the Record of the very Common-Prayer-Booke, as wee reade in the Preſace before the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation appointed to be read in the beginning of Lent. Brethren in the Primitive Church there was a godly Diſcipline, that at the beginning of Lent, ſuch perſons as were notorious ſinners were put to open Pennance. In the ſtead whereof untill the ſaid Diſcipline may be reſtored againe, (which thing is much to be wiſhed) it is thought good at this time, &amp;c. Was ſuch a godly Diſcipline ſo long agoe wiſhed to be reſtored, and ſhall it now be oppoſed? Either it was wiſhed in fincerity, or in hypocrifie; if in hypocrifie, why ſhould it be printed? If in ſincerity, why ſhould it not be effected? Should it ever be in wiſhing, and never brought to perfection? Parliaments were onely ſtately Pageants, if they ſhould onely confirme, and not alſo reforme old Lawes. If thou didſt not halt in the Parliaments Election, why ſhouldſt thou halt now, for feare what they ſhall doe, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in Nations Reformation, that Truth may ſucceed in the roome of errour, and Chriſts Kingdome brought into the Land with more puritie, and power, both for Doctrine, and Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Diſeſtimation of the Parliament, keepes men cold in the Common Cauſe, men thinke their power too great over their Purſes and Eſtates.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>9</hi> Cau.</note> On a time the members of the body cald a Counſell of Warre, to conſult why the ſtomacke devoured all; what ever the eye did ſee, the hand reach, the mouth conveyed it to the ſtomacke. Therefore they concluded to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare their accuſtomed offices and ſervices, ſeeing all tended onely to the benefit of the ſtomacke. In ſhort time it came to paſſe, that the eye began to wax dim, the hand weake, the feete feeble, and the mouth ſcaice able to open it ſelfe. They quickly ſaw their Error, and afforded their diligence in their wonted employments, and all was well againe, and they mutined no more. I need not ſpend time in making the application; If ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116086:21"/>ſhould have been denied to the Parliament, what had become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lawes, Liberties, Religion in the Kingdome?</p>
            <p>Wee hoped the Parliament would have ſetled Peace long before this time,<note place="margin">Object.</note> the Summer is gone, the winter come, and yet wee are not delivered, our ſhops are ſhut, or unaccuſtomed in the Citie, our grounds unſtocked, all Trading decayed in the Countrey?</p>
            <p>If the Lord ſend not Peace,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> can the Parliament procure it? Shall not they have a ſhare in it as well as any other? Are not their Eſtates as much if not more ruined than others are? 'Tis true, Peace is a fine thing, a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Bleſſing of God, then which nothing can be named with more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe, deſired with more heartineſſe, and obtained with more conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe, yet there is a certain thing, which they call Truth, which was ready to be baniſhed out of theſe Coaſts; and would outward Peace be much worth without Truth? Is not Peace of Conſcience an excellent Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, which who ever enjoyes, hath a continuall feaſt? Is not Peace with God, able to keepe our hearts and minds free from all feare of plundering, and aſſaults of enemies? Doth not this paſſe all underſtanding? Is it not a glorious ſight to ſee Righteouſneſſe and Peace kiſſe each other. Therefore the Prophet commands;<note place="margin">Zach. 8.19. V. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Love Truth and Peace:</hi> Truth you ſee is put in the firſt place. <hi>Therefore execute Truth and Peace in your Gates;</hi> implying the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the one as well as the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If it be poſſible have peace with all men;</hi> but that is not approved poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is oppoſite againſt pietie.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
               <hi>Follow peace and holineſſe with all, elſe you ſhall not ſee God. What God hath joyned together, Man muſt not put aſunder.</hi> Peace with men will little profit, whiles wee profeſſe and practiſe warre againſt God.</p>
            <p>The injuſtice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>10</hi> Cauſe.</note> oppreſſion, tyranny, and unreformation of Countrey Committees, cauſe people to continue in a ſtaggering eſtate, both for their opinions and Purſes in the Common Cauſe. Becauſe thoſe that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be inſtrumentall meanes to relieve, doe much grieve the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Yet Preachers before the high Court of Parliament cry out daily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Injuſtice; Maſter <hi>Caſe</hi> in his Sermon before the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, intreats them for the Lords ſake, to have a care, that none under the charge of the Parliament may be oppreſſed by their inſeriour Committees, leaſt people oppreſſed have occaſion to ſay, <hi>You have pulled down one Starre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, and have ſet up an hundred.</hi> Maſter <hi>Cheynell</hi> preaching before the Lords, <hi>March</hi> 27, upon the Pſalme, <hi>Man being in honour, &amp;c.</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Lords, intreats their Wiſdomes to have a care for the purging of Committees in <hi>Eſſex, Suſſex, Surrey,</hi> and <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> (I thinke his Petition might have extended towards all the Committees in the Kingdome) and he ſaid, that the ſpring was a fit time to give them Phyſicke, yet people ſee,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116086:21"/>none either given or taken, or working effectually upon them in reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They begin to halt in their opinions, and to be cold in their former aeale for the Cauſe: Which indeed reflects upon the honour of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as moyſture in the feete ſtrikes up into the head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cambyſes</hi> a King cauſed <hi>Sycanus</hi> a Judge (that had been hired by money to pronounce a wrong ſentence) to be flead, and his skinne to be hanged on the Judgement-ſeate, to be a torror to ſucceeding Judges. I thinke if ſome Committee-men were ſo uſed, they would have as little skinne left upon their backs, as ſome of them have land in the Countrey where they execute their Commiſſions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ethiopians</hi> were wont to ſet up a Chaire of State in their Senate, and that to be empty, as if the God of Judgement ſate there to be Umpire and Moderator, whom the Senators ought to looke upon in paſſing ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that they might immitate him in Judgement. The Lords in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Houſe have an emptie Chaire now in the abſence of the King, and yet not wholly empty, if they conſider the preſence of the King of Kings, that obſerves and heares all their Conſultations. I wiſh that County Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees might have an empty Chaire before them, to put them in minde that there is a power above them, to wit, the Parliament, and a power above that, the God of Heaven: If ſome Countrey Committee-Members, were ſet in a lower Chaire, and bound therein, and kept without bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter twenty-foure houres together, and had their unjuſt actions and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences writ before them in Capitall Letters, with <hi>mementomori,</hi> engraven on the upper Chaire; I beleeve if they were left to be their own Judges, they would paſſe ſentence of condemnation againſt themſelves. But this is a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> becauſe they are by Ordinance of Parliament, they thinke people will dare as ſoone adventure to enter into a Peſt houſe, as to endeavour any thing againſt them; yet to keepe people from deſpaire of all redreſſe herein, ſome Pamphletters have written (beſides what Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers have pulpitted) that there is as great neceſſitie for the new moulding of Committees, as there was of the Armies; who ſince they have been new moulded, the warres have proſpered the better; ſo it is to be hoped, if there were a new moulding of Committees, Juſtice would be better executed, Gods wrath ſooner appeaſed, the Parliament more honoured, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more contented.</p>
            <p>Which people let them be informed, that as the honorable Houſe have ſet out an Order that it ſhall be accounted an acceptable ſervice to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to an appointed Committee for that purpoſe, what money directly or indirectly hath been received by any Members of the Houſe for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of Juſtice; ſo it is beleeved that they intend to ſet out an Order of like acceptable ſervices for any man before that or ſome other Committee,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116086:22"/>to diſcover the injuſtice, oppreſſion, partialitie, connivency (towards Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants) of any Members in County-Committees, as a ſpeciall preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive againſt peoples halting and railing in theſe Realme-reeling times.</p>
            <p>Flattery in,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>11</hi> Cau.</note> and diviſions between Miniſters, make people to hale; Paint a fire on a piece of cloath, and caſt it into the water, you heare no noiſe, no hiſſing, becauſe no combate of contrary natures; but caſt a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Coale into the water, you heare a ratling, a noiſe, which proceeds from the combate, or encounter of two contraries, the one ſtriving to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the other: The end of Gods Word is to reforme the judgement, and life; Gods Word is true, and every man a lyar, <hi>(i)</hi> erroneous in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and life; when truth and falſhood, the word of God and the word of men doe meete, then beginnes the Conflict: The one labours to deſtroy the other: Gods word is as fire, mens affections as water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> preached at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he ſcattered true fire among them; <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſtartles at it, and ſtirres up ſedition among the people, there the contrary roares and ratles; In comes the Towne-Clerke with the magnificence of <hi>Diana, Great is Diana of the Epheſians;</hi> a falſe fire, a counterfeit fire, there is no oppoſition, no contradiction at all made againſt him: It is juſt the caſe of our times; if Preachers come (as commonly they doe) now, more than ever (becauſe they ſpare mens vices to favour mens perſons, and fill their own purſes) with a painted fire, ſowing pillows under the arme-holes of ſinners, crying, peace, peace, take it upon any termes, you muſt doe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the King would have you doe; will you have Biſhops (whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors were Martyrs for the truth) to be ſuppreſſed? Keep up the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Booke, and then without much paines you may know how to pray as well as Miniſters themſelves: If Preachers thus ſtroake the ſpleene with ſugred words, and tickle the eare with quaint phraſes, and rub it with filken words, ſaying, Becauſe you are predeſtinated, you ſhall goe to Heaven, as men carried in a Coach, or ſayling in a Ship, without any action or motion of their own, they ſhall ſeldome be gainſaid; but if Miniſters come with a true fire, with <hi>a worke out your ſalvation with feare and trembling,</hi> with an <hi>yet fortie dayes, and Niniveb ſhall be deſtroyed;</hi> with a <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> cry, <hi>Now is the Axe laid to the roote of the tree; Now,</hi> inſtantly; <hi>is,</hi> certainly; <hi>the Axe,</hi> inſtrumentally; <hi>laid,</hi> orderly; <hi>to the roote,</hi> effectually; <hi>of the tree,</hi> particularly; <hi>Every tree,</hi> impartially; <hi>that bringeth not forth,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally; <hi>good fruit,</hi> proportionably; <hi>is,</hi> unavoydably; <hi>hewen,</hi> fearfully; <hi>downe,</hi> fatally; <hi>and caſt,</hi> unreſiſtably; <hi>into the fire,</hi> everlaſtingly: If Miniſters caſt ſuch coales, then people beginne to murmure, becauſe their affections are but watery; the word in the mouthes of ſuch Miniſters laboure to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy finne in the people, and the finne of the people labours to deſtroy the word in the mouth of the Miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:116086:22"/>If flattering Miniſters have ſeduced the King, many Nobles, many Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Houſe, have not the ſtanding ones then great cauſe to look to themſelves, that they alſo be not miſ-lead, by having mens perſons in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, <hi>Tune tua res agitur, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was ever the ſubtilty of Satan to imploy flattering Prophets, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers for the ſeducing of Princes and people.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.2.</note> There were falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets among the people, mingling noyſome weeds among ſweet flowers; By reaſon of whom the way of truth was ill ſpoken of, the Goſpel reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and others perverted. As long as the Devill hath his Kingdome here, he ſends abroad his Emiſſaries to ſeduce the people. Hence it is,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1.</note> that the man of fin is come to ſo great a height by ſeducing Spirits.</p>
            <p>The Devill and the Pope have many induſtrious Chaplaines, boaſting as if they were inſpired and ſent from God; Firſt, ſcruing themſelves into mens Conſciences, and then picking their purſes, Cheating them of their Religion and ſalvation, and then of their eſtates, obtruding guilded er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors inſtead of ſolid and golden truths. The Lord had decreed this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to great miſeries, for a puniſhment of the great abuſe of his mercies; and therefore ſuffered Satan to ſeduce Princes and people, and this by the helpe of ſeducing Preachers. God hath a quarrell againſt <hi>Ahab,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuffers him to be ingaged in ſuch a warre wherein he ſhall be undone. <hi>Who ſhall perſwade Ahab?</hi> Satan is at hand, <hi>I will perſwade Ahab?</hi> How? <hi>I will be a lying Spirit in the mouth of all his Prophets.</hi> Of all? (if there were foure hundred falſe Prophets to one <hi>Eliah</hi> in <hi>Ahabs</hi> time, no wonder of ſuch great diſproportion in theſe dayes.) The Devill knew the length of their foote, that he could prevalle with them, and they with the King. He knew <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel</hi> had a company of mercenary Miniſters, Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher Chaplaines, that would ſay any thing; unhappy <hi>Ahab,</hi> by reaſon of ſuch flatterers; Be therefore carefull to eſpie and oppoſe, but never won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or thinke ſtrange of the Devils policy to uſe flattering Preachers to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſtraiable people.</p>
            <p>They are the <hi>Paſtors of Gods flock;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Shepheard is ſtricken, the ſheep are ſcattered.</p>
            <p>They are the <hi>Stewards of Gods houſe;</hi> When the Stewards are unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the family will be ſtarved.</p>
            <p>They are the <hi>Captains of Gods Armie;</hi> When the Captain falls, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers will ſoone be put to flight.</p>
            <p>They are the <hi>lights of the world;</hi> if the Lamps be extinguiſhed, the houſe fits in darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>They are the <hi>ſalt of the earth;</hi> if the ſalt become unſavoury, the people are in danger to become a polluted and unſavoury ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>They commonly take all upon truſt from their Teachers, which cauſe them to halt (long too) between two opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116086:23"/>Theſe Saim uſeth as an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> to people in darkneſſe, and carries them headlong to their hurt, and halting, till they ſtumble and fall, and many times breake the necks of their ſalvation, by theſe ſtumbling blocks; Satan by his own power, can do great feates on people, much more by the power of Princes, and flattery of Paſtors.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles therefore were winnowed as wheat,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.31 2 Cor. 12.7. 1 Kings 13 18.30.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> buffeted by Satan; One Prophet may be ſeduced by another, if God aſſiſt not, or doe withdraw his Spirit; It's no wonder, that greene and young Spirits are miſ-lead, when old Prophets that pretend authoritie from God to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance their errors, have been ſeduced? Such ſeducing ones you ſee reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Devill; <hi>You are of your Father the Devill, for his works yee doe:</hi> From whom can they then expect wages, but from him, for whom they worke? To prevent this danger of halting in the people, it muſt be the care of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Paſtors, to lift up their voyces, to cry aloud; for my part, I know lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle uſe of Bells without clappers, Watch-men without eyes, Souldiers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out weapons, Preachers without crying, and Cryers without courage; They are but as Idolls that have eyes, and ſee not, mouthes and ſpeak not, ſuch cannot but be ſeduced that put their truſt in them.</p>
            <p>Travellers need prudent and faithfull Guids, eſpecially when they paſſe doubtfull and dangerous wayes; Safe and bold Convoyes requiſite in wayes beſet with many adverſaries; skilfull and couragious Pilotts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected when men are to glide between <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis,</hi> to encounter with multitude of Pirats. You heare of Antinomians, who deny the Law to be the Rule of life; Of Arminians, who undermine the Covenant of free grace, that they may gratifie free will; Of Anabaptiſts, who withhold Baptiſme, the Seale of that Covenant, from Infants, children of thoſe that are within that Covenant, of others that queſtion the truth of our Church and Miniſtrie, in and by which ſo many thouſands have been new borne unto God; of others that ſay, that there is no need of Miniſtrie, flattering us with hope of new Apoſtles, and glorious revelations.</p>
            <p>Have wee then not need of many <hi>Eliahs,</hi> that may ſhew skill and zeale in crying, <hi>Why halt you ſo long between ſo many opinions?</hi> Have they not need to warne againſt enemies, to direct againſt error by the light of the Word; Will not Satan uſe all meanes and methods to puzzle men in the miſts of new opinions, that ſo they may be miſ-lead, or cauſed to halt and fall by the many ſtumbling blocks he caſts in their way?</p>
            <p>I thinke the late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in that part of his own fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sermon, preached by himſelfe to that ample open Auditorie, ſpake this truth; <hi>That the Pope had never ſuch a harveſt in</hi> England <hi>ſince the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as he hath now by the ſects and diviſions that are among us;</hi> But he ſpake nothing of the hopes of the rooting out of the multiplicitie of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116086:23"/>by the power of Parliament. Who can tell, what light at length may breake forth, after theſe blacke and bloudy Clouds are ſcattered? Maſter <hi>Farrell</hi> was long oppoſed and threatned in the reformation of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and other Cities, yet did they then coyn money with this poſie on the one ſide; <hi>Poſt tenebras Lux;</hi> and on the other ſide; <hi>Deus pugnat cum nobis;</hi> I hope wee once may have cauſe to be ſuch coyne, notwithſtanding the numerous errors, diviſions, difficulties, dangers, yet hovering over our heads; God can eaſily rebuke Satan (as he did when he reſiſted <hi>Joſuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 3.1, 2</note> labouring a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) he knows how to conſute errors, to reſolve doubts, compoſe differences, conquer difficulties, remove dangers, with advantage to his own Cauſe, and wee may have peace after ſo many perturbations.<note place="margin">Eſa. 62.7.</note> Reſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long motions, and ſtabliſhment after ſuch quaſſations, and our Church and Kingdome may be made a praiſe on earth; and reape the harveſt of ſo many prayers ſowen in and for the ſame; yet the great diviſions amongſt Brethren, emulations between Miniſters, Presbyterian, Independents, cauſe heart-burning and judgement, halting among the people. Many people imagine ſome great myſtery of Atheiſme now broached, that was never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed before; When they have heard Preachers ſo oft perſwade to love and unity among people, yet they themſelves to perſonate and practice ſo much envy, hatred, and fiery contentions, which ſeeme to caſt oyle on the fire ſo mightily flaming in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>It is good to be zealous alwayes in a good matter; But there is a time for all things; A word in ſeaſon, &amp;c. Should not all labour to quench a common fire, rather than coutend who ſhall have the goods in the houſe, if it be not burned? Should not the Marriners row hard, to bring the Ship to ſhoare, rather than ſtrive about trimming the Cabinets, or divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fraught, in the midſt of a ſtorme? Should not the ſick man be more carefull to recover from his diſeaſe, than in the midſt of his ſickneſſe to be curious for this, or that trimming on his apparrell? The whole three Kingdomes are ſick, by ſinne, ſorrowes, ſufferings; Should not remedies be ſought, rather than the miſeries augmented? Sheep wandring heere and there, when they ſee the Wolfe comming they run apace and flock toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Two Maſtiffs fighting, and not by men partable, yet if a Lyon or Beare approach, they part of themſelves. The Turk the Pope endeavour the Kingdomes deſtruction, ſhould not Independents, Presbyterians, All good Proteſtants, unite their heads, hands, hearts, tongues, pens, all, for the conſervation of themſelves, and the whole Land? Men muſt contend for the truth, prove all things, and hold that which is good; Is it not a good, a joyfull thing to ſee Brethren to dwell together in unity? It is like <hi>Aarons</hi> oyle, if it fall from theſe heads the Paſtors, It will deſcend to the beards and bodies of the people, yea to all the skirts of the Kingdome;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116086:24"/>If the Anti-Parliament Army ſhould approach and aſſault the beſieging of the great City (which God forbid) the greateſt part being but Neutralls, many ſtrong Malignants, and too many Papiſts in the ſame, if either ſide of the now much divided and ſtrong contending Brethren, ſhould aſſiſt ſo many inveterate enemies within, would it not mightily encourage the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulting forces and foes without? O therefore pray, and preach, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in generall, and of theſe three Nations in particular. They ſurely ſhall proſper that love ſo to pray, preach, practice, becauſe the well being of any thing, depends on the being of the ſame: Should not all ſeek the peace of the Citie, Kingdome, as knowing, that they themſelves ſhall have peace in the peace thereof? Miniſters, People, Presbyterians, Independents, all ſhould have peace in the peace of the Land, and this Land and many other Nations are in more probabilitie to have publique peace, in the private peace of theſe warring brethren. Doe not wee ſee the whole three Kingdomes (in the Parliament) lie as a Traytor upon the blocke, ready to have the head thereof ſtrucke off, at one bloudy blow? For as the King is head in regard of the Parliament, ſo the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is head in relation to the Countrey; and is this a time to nouriſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions amongſt any of thoſe who ſhould ſtudie the peace of the Publique? The dogge is ſometime let out to keepe the ſheepe together; our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments many times carry our ſinnes in their foreheads, our diviſions, have been, ſtill are great, contentions increaſe, God puniſheth our diviſions with diviſions; The water leads to the fountaine whence it flowes; God points to our ſinne, by our puniſhments; that by puniſhment ſinne may be cured, and after the Judgements may be removed: Wee would ſeperate from Gods houſe, God ſeperates us from our own houſes; Wee cared not for the worth of peace, God now ſhewes the worth by the want of it, (the price of many things are learn't <hi>carendo magis quàm fruendo,</hi>) Wee walked contrary unto him, he now walkes contrary unto us: Wee brake forth, by lying, ſtealing, whoring, one bloudy ſinne touched another, and now God hath had a long Controverſie againſt all the Inhabitants of the Land, and one bloudy puniſhment toucheth another; Men by their Hell-haſtening iniquities warred, brake forth againſt the Lord, and now God by Heaven-darting Judgements warreth againſt, and breaketh in upon men; Yea, this heighteneth mens ſinnes, that they warre againſt the Lord; yea, friends againſt friends, whiles God and man continue their warre againſt them both; God in Juſtice, men in hatred, tis good, as from God, evill, as from men: I have ſpoken ſo much in this point, it being a maine cauſe of halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the people, while they apprehend ſo much flattery in, and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among Miniſters; Let all <hi>Eliah's</hi> labour to preſerve people from halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by occaſion thereof; Let them ſtudy to keepe the unity of the Spirit in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116086:24"/>the Bond of peace; if there be any vertue, any praiſe, any profit, in love, in peace: <hi>Elijah</hi> you ſee was bold, and it mightily prevailed; Can Miniſters write after any fairer Copie, can they walke after any more un-erring Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be ſtrong and of a good courage,</hi> was Gods Counſell to <hi>Joſuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 1.6.</note> and addes in the next verſe; <hi>onely be ſtrong;</hi> and the people cloſe up their Counſell with the ſame Caution to him in the laſt words of the ſame Chapter (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe things laſt of all ſpoken,<note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> commonly are beſt of all remembred) <hi>onely be ſtrong, and of a good courage,</hi> verſ. 18. As if courage, boldneſſe, were the All in All, required in the Leaders, the Shepheards of Gods flocke; as if it were the Quinteſſence that is moſt to be ſeene, in the eſſence of all their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, and diſcharge of duties required by God and Man, may they not by this their courage, (as <hi>Hannibal</hi> by ſire over the Alpes) make way over the mountaines of all obſtructions, all oppoſitions whatſoever? Look what powder is to bullets, a clapper to the Bell, fire to the wood, wings to a Bird, ſayles to a Ship, winde to ſayles, wine to the ſpirits, an edge to a Razor, mettall to a horſe, the ſoule to the body, vivacitie to any creature, the ſame is Courage to any Chriſtian, much more to a Miniſter; for his affection, motion, action.</p>
            <p>Twelfth and laſt cauſe I mention of the Peoples halting,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>12.</hi> Cauſe.</note> between the two maine opinions in theſe times, is, <hi>The doubt of the ſucceſſe of the Cauſe in Queſtion;</hi> which followes in the laſt, not leaſt place to be anſwered; <hi>viz.</hi> theſe Doores of Hope.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> DOORES OF HOPE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat ever the iſſue and ſucceſſe of theſe warres be, yet Gods people ſhould be of <hi>Joabs</hi> reſolution;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Let us be valiant for our people, and for the Cities of our God; and let the Lord do, as ſeemeth him good.</hi> I am no Prophet, nor the ſon of a Prophet, ungain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayably to prognoſticate the event; his face hath never yet been ſeene, nor tongue heard in a Pulpit, that can thus Divine: Therefore I will not profeſſe ſo much ignorance or arrogance peremptorily to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch, Theſe preſent warres ſuddenly ſhall end, or that the Parliament ſide, without any poſſible contradiction ſhall prevaile; But this I affirme, that there may be alledged many Arguments of probabilitie, that God will ſhortly deliver this Land from Popery and ſlavery, for the preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture time. Theſe Arguments I call Doores of Hope; Of which Doores I ſhall but draw the Latches, and ſet them a little aſhoare, and give you leave
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116086:25"/>at your more leiſure to goe into the ſeverall roomes in your private medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and view the materialls therein contained.</p>
               <p>The firſt,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> I bring you to, is the Promiſe of God made to comfort his people;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4. Eſa. 25.8.</note> Theſe promiſes are ſaid, <hi>to be Gods gifts, many, great, exceeding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; The Lord will wipe away teares from off all faces, and the rebuke of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall he take away from off all the earth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 14.8.</note> for the <hi>Lord hath ſpoken it. Babylon is fallen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 55.10.</note> 
                  <hi>is fallen;</hi> Doubled (as <hi>Phar:</hi> dreame) for the certainty of the thing: <hi>Shall the Lord promiſe, and ſhall he not performe? Surely, as the raine cometh downe, and watereth the earth, and makes it bring forth, and bud, that it may give ſeede to the ſower, and bread to him that eateth; So ſhall my word be, that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of my mouth; it ſhall not returne unto mee voyde, but it ſhall accompliſh that which I will, and it ſhall proſper in the thing, whereto I ſent it.</hi> Its added in the next verſe;<note place="margin">Verſ. 11. Ioſ. 21.43.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore ſhall yee goe out with joy, and be led forth with peace.</hi> This Argument couragious <hi>Joſuah</hi> propoſed a little before his death, to continue the people in conſtancy; <hi>The Lord gave Iſrael all the land, which he had</hi> ſworne <hi>to give to their Fathers, and they poſſeſſed it, and dwelt therein.</hi> Verſ. 44. <hi>Alſo the Lord gave them reſt round about, aocording</hi> to all that he had ſworne unto their Fathers; <hi>and there ſtood not a man of all their Enemies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; for the Lord delivered all their Enemies into their hand.</hi> Verſ. 45. <hi>There</hi> failed nothing <hi>of all the good things, which the Lord had ſaid unto the houſe of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 45. Ch. 23.14.</note> but all came to paſſe. And in the next Chap. 14. verſe, to the people; <hi>You know in all your hearts</hi> (as certainly as if things were in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome) <hi>that</hi> nothing hath failed <hi>of all the good things, which the Lord your God promiſed you, but</hi> all are <hi>come to paſſe unto you:</hi> nothing hath failed thereof. The Lord commands his Prophets,<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.1, 2</note> 
                  <hi>Comfort yee, comfort yee my people, ſpeake comfortably unto Jeruſalem, and cry unto her, that her warfare is accompliſhed.</hi> Where you ſee, is a Charge and Commiſſion given, not onely by bare affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, or command to Miniſters, but by Ingemination, <hi>Comfort yee, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort yee;</hi> yea, by Triplication, <hi>ſpeake yee comfortably unto Jeruſalem;</hi> by Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druplication, <hi>and cry unto her, that her warfare is accompliſhed: is,</hi> i. it ſhall as certainly be accompliſhed, as if it were already effected. Theſe comfortable promiſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin</hi> on Eſay.</note> muſt not be whiſpered ſoftly in their eares, ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> but cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out aloud, that they may ſinke into their hearts. Let us make uſe of theſe promiſes in our prayers,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.49, 50.</note> ſaying with <hi>David; Remember thy promiſe made to thy ſervant, wherein thou haſt cauſed mee to truſt: It is my comfort in my trouble, for thy promiſe hath quickned mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gods Providence and Power in the Lands preſervation.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doore</hi> 2.</note> What are the Mightie, againſt the Almightie? The Nations of the Earth, are as a drop hanging on the Bucket of water. What is a drop, to the Bucket? What the Bucket, to all the water in the Well? What all the water, to the whole Sea? What the Sea, to him, that made Sea and Land, Heaven and Hell, men and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116086:25"/>Devils? Winde, Waters, Heaven, Earth, Men, Devills muſt obey him. In compariſon of whoſe power, all the Nations of the Earth,<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.17.</note> are not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as a drop of water, but leſſe than nothing.</p>
               <p>The Lord hath manifeſted his power and providence againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Water-workes in 88. and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Fire-workes, in 1605 and his hand is not ſhortened now? The Kingdome, is as it were, on a light fire, but as the Buſh in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, burning, yet not conſumed? why and how ſo?<note place="margin">Exod. 3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord appeared in the flame:</hi> Where Gods preſence is in a Buſh, a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, an Army, a Kingdome, though all may burne, yet can they not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.<note place="margin">Eſa. 43.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare not, O Jacob, when thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee; the floods ſhall not overflow thee. When thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, the kindled flame, ſhall not kindle upon thee, for I am the Lord thy God. It is of the Lords mercies, that wee are not conſumed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 3.22. Eſa. 54.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>What it added? <hi>Becauſe his compaſſions faile not. For a moment, have I hid my face from thee, in mine anger, for a little ſeaſon,</hi> a little ſeaſon, a moment, the one explaining the other; <hi>but with everlaſting mercie, have I had campaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer. For a little while have I forſaken thee, but with great compaſſion will I gather thee. For this</hi> (Kingdome) <hi>is unto mee as the waters of Noah; for as I have ſworne, that the waters of Noah, ſhall no more goe over the Earth, ſo have I ſworne, &amp;c. Behold, the enemy ſhall gather himſelfe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>but without mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoever</hi> (not exempting any, be they never ſo potent or politique) <hi>ſhall gather himſelfe in thee,</hi> (in muſtering forces, and thundering threatnings) <hi>againſt thee ſhall fall. All the weapons that are made againſt thee, ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper:</hi> Why?<note place="margin">Verſ. 17. Verſ. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold, I have created the Smith, and his Inſtrument:</hi> I have power to order and diſpoſe of all men and matters, even the blowing of the coales in the fire. <hi>Without mee, they can doe nothing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.33.</note> No weapon ſhall prevaile with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my will. <hi>In the world, yee ſhall have affliction, but ſaith Chriſt, I have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The two Nations Aſſociation in the Bond or Covenant,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Lawes, Liberties of the two Kingdomes. <hi>Voe ſoli,</hi> woe to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if alone; Danger to neither, if they hold firme. A threefold corde, is not eaſily broken; nor a twofold, if God ties them together. Collonell <hi>Carre,</hi> when he was aſſaulted to betray his Truſt, anſwered the Tempters; <hi>He was a Covenanter, Therefore could not breake it.</hi> The Cauſe hath been the more ſucceſsfull, ſince the Covenant hath been taken; If more had taken (and kept being taken) the ſaid Covenant and Vow, the Papiſts would have feared it more, than the Proteſtants doe their Popes holy water.</p>
               <p>The undaunted Reſolution of the Nobles,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, the body of the Kingdome; they have yet ſtood, maugre the malice of Atheiſts, Papiſts, and all other their oppoſers whatſoever. The
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116086:26"/>
                  <hi>Philiſtims</hi> aſſembled,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.11.</note> at a Towne, where was a piece of a field full of Lentils, and the people fled from the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> But he ſtood in the midſt of the field, and defended it, and ſlew the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> for the <hi>Lord gave a great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi> It is of Gods great mercy (notwithſtanding ſo many revolters, that betrayed their truſt) to keep the reſt ſo firme, as one man, with their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to uphold the reeling Realme; and to encourage one another, in <hi>Joabs</hi> words;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.12. 1 Sam. 6.10.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Let us be valiant for our people, Cities, &amp;c.</hi> Wee reade, touching the carrying of the Arke to <hi>Bethſhemeſh, That they took two kine, and tyed them to the Cart, and the Kine went the ſtreight way to Bethſhemeſh, and kept one path, and lowed as they went, and turned neither to the right hand, nor to the left.</hi> I think I need not beſpeake your pardon, in the application, for the homeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the compariſon; The Arke of God, wee hope is in tranſportation from the Popiſh <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> to be reſtored to its ancient puritie and power, both for Doctrine and Diſcipline; its tyed to the two honorable Houſes; Thoſe whom God hath promoted to theſe publique places, hath he indued with publique Spirits. As the Kine lowed after their calves tyed at home, and much more the calves after the Kine gone abroad; ſo theſe Peeres and Patriots, have fleſh and bloud about them, (as well as Spirit in them) to hanker after their pleaſures and profits, wives and children, their freſh aire, their ſpacious houſes, ſpecious Gardens, choice dyets, daily attendants, familiar friends and acquaintances, from which for a long while they have been deprived; yet through divine aſſiſtance, their ſpirits are overpowred, have kept one path for the carrying home the Arke, (without turning to the right hand, or to the left,) to maintain the Goſpel of Chriſt, the Lawes of the Kingdome, and the libertie of the Subject, though they have been denied outward liberty or life to returne to their native habitations, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted delights and enjoyments. Shall not our men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh,</hi> rejoyce more, at the approach of the Arke, than for the abundance of their crop, in their wheate harveſt?<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> Is it not great hope, the Arke of peace and piety will be brought fully home, to the Kingdome, when it is within kenne of the Inhabitants?</p>
               <p>The returne of ſome eminent perſons to tender their ſervice to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> after they had been at the <hi>Oxonian Juncto,</hi> where they meerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted their own honour, or advanced the hopes of the Royaliſts. Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Deering</hi> confeſſed (as I related already) under his own hand in Print, that the <hi>King with forty men might come to Weſtminſter, and ſtay there with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted ſafetie to his perſon; ſo</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I ſaid while I was at</hi> Oxford, <hi>and doe ſtill aſſuredly beleeve ſo, and God will bleſſe him, if he doe ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did not God, and his Conſcience, enforce this confeſtion? <hi>He much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at himſelfe, how he could ſo long be tranſported to aſſiſt in a way, to deſtroy that Parliament, which he had tooke the Proteſtation in Parliament to preſerve.</hi> Ponder well the ſpeech of this Perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116086:26"/>The many Prayers, Faſtings, Teares,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> for the ſucceſſe of the Common Cauſe. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> told <hi>Monica, Auguſtines</hi> Mother, that it could not be, A Woman, or Mother of ſo many Teares and Prayers, ſhould bring forth a Sonne to be loſt. It cannot be, that an Aſſembly, a Parliament, a Kingdome of ſo many Faſts, Prayers, Teares, brought and kept with ſo much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie together, ſhould miſcarry. God, that hath prepared <hi>Englands</hi> hearts to pray, hath prepared his eare to heare.<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, thou haſt heard the deſire of the humble; Thou wilt prepare their heart; Thou wilt cauſe thine eare to heare, to helpe the fatherleſſe, and oppreſſed, that the men of the Earth may no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themſelves. Manoah ſaid to his wife, Wee ſhall ſurely dye.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 13.22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>But his wife ſaid unto him; If the Lord would kill us, he would not have received a meate offering, and a burnt offering at our hands, neither would he have ſhewed, or told us all theſe things;</hi> that theſe Devile (in the likeneſſe of men, yet very Monſters) could no otherwiſe be caſt forth, but by prayer and faſting. Therefore hath the Lord God made ſo many &amp; precious promiſes, that his people might have their ſpirits kept up, and they learne to truſt in him for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes</hi> (who hath appointed theſe as ſpeciall wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in the times of warre) <hi>the faſt of the fourth moneth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 8.19.</note> 
                  <hi>and the faſt of the fifth, and the faſt of the ſeventh, and the faſt of the tenth moneth, ſhall be to the houſe of Judah, joy and gladneſſe, and proſperous high feaſts.</hi> Therefore obſerve with care and conſcience ſuch feaſts, as you deſire to ſhew your love to Truth and peace. For if ſuch Faſtes of foure ſeverall moneths obſerving, have ſuch promiſes, What harveſt of hope ſhall the ſeeds of twenty foure moneths faſting bring forth, when they come to the yeares of perfection? Were not the <hi>Jewes</hi> faſting dayes, in the time of Queene <hi>Eſther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſt. 8.16, 17 and 9.22.</note> turned to them from ſorrow to joy, and from mourning into joyfull dayes, and times of feaſting; Wherein they had occaſion to ſend preſente every man to his neighbour, and gifts to the poore? in comemoration of Gods bounty ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them in their poore and low condition. The neglecters of ſuch dayes of faſting, have profeſſed themſelves Traytors to the State, and whole Kingdome.</p>
               <p>The many Blaſphemies and villanies of the enemies,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> doe foretell Gods Juſtice approaching, and his hand ready to be reached forth, to caſt them into that pit they have digged for others. A Popiſh Doctor of Phyſicke confeſſed, that the Catholike Cauſe never ſuffered ſo much diſhonour, as by that barbarous cruelty that was ſhewed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the ſavage murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of men. When the Towne of <hi>Bolton</hi> was taken, <hi>Where is the Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads God now,</hi> ſaid one of them? <hi>Surely he is turned Cavalier. I give this Roundhead one blow more,</hi> ſaid another, <hi>to ſend him quickly to the Devill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They bad <hi>William Boulton,</hi> (whom they found praying) <hi>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all on his God to ſave him. Yonder lyes one of the ſtrongeſt Roundheads,</hi> ſaid the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116086:27"/>
                  <hi>that ever I met with; For one of my Piſtols diſcharged at his heart would not enter, but I thinke, I ſent him to the Devill with a vengeance, with the other.</hi> Oh Heaven, oh Earth, oh <hi>England,</hi> oh the Judge of all, beare witneſſe of this calamitie, crueltie, Blaſphemie, when thou makeſt inquiſition after bloud.</p>
               <p>The patience of Gods people,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> notwithſtanding all Souldiers Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all their Payments, all their Plunderings, Bondage, Impriſonments, Mockings, Deaths. Here is the Patience of the Saints, not onely to beare witneſſe to the Truth, but alſo that they are objects of Deliverance. Where the Precept is;<note place="margin">Phil. 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Be yee patient;</hi> the promiſe is added; <hi>For the Lord is at hand;</hi> not onely to ſee, but alſo to helpe. When Gods ſervants, humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under his hand, with patient ſubmiſſion to his correction, ſaying, <hi>He hath ſpoyled, and he will heale us; he hath wounded, and he will binde us up;</hi> Faith ſteps in,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1, 2.</note> to aſſure them, that <hi>after two dayes,</hi> (<hi>i.</hi> a ſhort time) <hi>he will revive them, and in the third day he will raiſe them, and they ſhall live in his ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Liberalitie of the <hi>Londoners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doore <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> and others, for the Publique Cauſe; Many have done much, without compulſion; <hi>the love of Chriſt,</hi> Religion, Kingdome, (as well as their own liberties, lives) <hi>conſtrained them.</hi> I heard ſome Citizens ſay, they had done thus, and thus, in ſeverall Disburſements, and yet beleeve, they had not the leſſe, becauſe God bleſſed the reſt the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Some ſaid, ſince the loſſe in the Weſt, they would lend more than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; They that ſowed ſo plentifully, feared not to reape ſparingly.</p>
               <p>The Diſcovery of ſo many Plots,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> touching the whole Land, <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Parliament, <hi>London,</hi> and many other particular places, and perſons, have infallibly demonſtrated, Surely the finger of the Lord was in them; All In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers in the world could not have diſcovered more, than hath been revealed. If the Lord would have deſtroyed the Kingdome, would he have ſhewed,<note place="margin">Iudg. 13.23</note> and revealed, ſuch, and ſuch things? Though the woman was weak in ſexe, yet was ſhee ſtronger in Faith herein, than was her husband.</p>
               <p>The many ſucceſsfull Victories;<note place="margin">Doore <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> when few have diſcomfited many, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the aſſiſtance by Papiſts, and prophane ones, ſecretly and openly againſt our Armies. The many Armies of Gods Saints prayed marching before, and piercing the Heavens for helpe: Scarce any Faſt in publique obſerved, but thereon people were mightily encouraged to meete the Lord in prayers, that daily met them even on thoſe dayes, with new mercies, and matter of praiſes; the Faſts have been ſweetned with figues of feaſting; which occaſioned our Forces in the Field, to implore the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Interceſſions of the Saints unto the Lord of Hoſtes for helpe.<note place="margin">Zach. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Who art thou, that deſpiſeſt the Day of ſmall things?</hi> Its hopefull, that thoſe that have forſaken all for God, ſhall never be forſaken by God; he that hath
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116086:27"/>wrought ſo on their hearts, can and will worke more by their hands. As this Countie is almoſt cleared of rude and robbing perſons, ſo may ſhortly the whole Kingdome be delivered. <hi>He that hath delivered us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10.</note> 
                  <hi>doth deliver,</hi> in him wee truſt, that he alſo will deliver the whole Nation.</p>
               <p>The great oppoſition by Princes, Prieſts, People, preſage great mercies,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> to enſue great miſeries. When ſhe ayre is ſharpeſt, the weather is nigheſt breaking; When the night is darkeſt, the dayes dawning is neareſt; When the Womans Throubbes are thickeſt, her delivery is ſpeedieſt. Violent things, are not of long continuance.<note place="margin">1 King. 1 34. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> will call for water out of the foure Barrells that were filled, and cauſed the ſame, once, twice, yea the third time, to be powred on the wood, and on the Sacrifice, and the whole Ditch alſo to be filled with water, and then the fire from Heaven ſhall come downe, and conſume the burnt-offering, and the wood, and the ſtones, and the duſt, and licked up the water that was in the Ditch; So powerfull is God to reſiſt the greateſt reſiſtances, that Nature, Men, or Devils can make againſt the ſmalleſt number of his Saints; ſo that all the people fell on their faces, and were enforced to cry, <hi>The Lord, is God, the Lord, is God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Kings of the Earth ſtand up,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and the Princes take Counſell together, againſt the Lord his Chriſt, his Church; <hi>When the Heathen rage, and the people murmure, ſaying, Let us breake their Bonds, and caſt their cords away from us,</hi> all is in vaine; <hi>He that dwelleth in Heaven ſhall laugh, &amp;c. and breake them in pieces, &amp;c.</hi> The Ten Kings ſhall have one minde,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.1.</note> to yeeld all their might to helpe the monſtrous Beaſt, <hi>that was, and is not, and yet is;</hi> all theſe ſhall fight with the Lambe, yet the Lambe ſhall overcome. The Lambe overcome? What is a Lambe to a Lyon, to many Lyons? <hi>The wrath of a King is as the roaring of a Lyon, and is the meſſenger of death:</hi> yet the Lambe ſhall overcome; and a good Reaſon is rendred;<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>For he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings;</hi> and they that are on his ſide, are called, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and faithfull.</p>
               <p>The Great Light of the Goſpel, and the many converted thereby.<note place="margin">Doore <hi>13</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The light ſhineth more, and more, till perfect day.</hi> Cutting of Trees, and Stones, hewing of both, a good ſigne, God is about to build.<note place="margin">Act. 7.17</note> When the time of the promiſe drew nigh for <hi>Iſraels</hi> deliverance, the people grew, and multiplyed in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Shall Gods fold be increaſed, to fatten the ſword of his enemies? Gods ſheepe may be affrighted, muſt not be deſtroyed.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6.</note> If barrenneſſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth deſtruction, then fruitfulneſſe ſignifies preſervation. <hi>Sing, O Barren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 54.1, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>that didſt not beare, and breake forth on the right hand, and on the left, and thy ſeede ſhall inherite the Gentiles, and make the deſolate Cities to be inhabited. Feare not, for thou ſhalt not be aſhamed; Thou ſhalt not remember the reproach of thy widdowhood any more. For thy maker is thy husband,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap 60.21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord of Hoſts is his Name. Thy people ſhall be all righteous, the Branch of my Planting, the worke of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116086:28"/>my hands, that I may be glorified. A little one ſhall become a thouſand</hi> (a great augmentation) <hi>and a ſmall one a ſtrong Nation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſay 66.9.</note> 
                  <hi>I the Lord will haſten it in his time. Shall I cauſe to travell, and not bring forth? Shall I cauſe to bring forth, and ſhall it be barren, ſaith thy God? Reigne with Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> When plants are put into Gods Orchard, ſhall they not by him be preſerved? Shall the Church have many children,<note place="margin">Pſa. 127.5.</note> as ſo many Quivers of Arrowes in her hand, and ſhall ſhe be aſhamed of her enemy in the gate?</p>
               <p>Gods daily Remembrancers,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> both in private and in publick, which are commanded by himſelfe to give him no reſt, night or day, till he make <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem a praiſe on the earth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 62.7.</note> God will beſtow a mercy when he comes to be minded of it. When the ſeventy yeares were nigh accompliſhed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance fully to be wrought,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 29.</note> God ſet <hi>Daniel</hi> on praying, which was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by <hi>Jeremy:</hi> Are not ſuch prayers too pretious to be loſt? Shall ſuch Watchmen be made a prey to the enemies? Shall we imagine, that God that raiſeth ſuch inſtruments for his Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, will ſuffer the ſame to be blaſted? Shall <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Phineas</hi> (raiſed by God to ſtand up in the gap to ſave Gods people) be unſucceſsfull? When <hi>Moſes</hi> hands were lift up, <hi>Iſrael</hi> prevailed; when let downe, the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekites</hi> prevailed.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 17.11.</note> If our ſinnes blaſt not the bloſſomes of our Prayers, they ſhall prevaile with God for our ſelves and others. For hath not prayer been an Engine ordained by God himſelfe to overcome himſelfe? <hi>Let me alone,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> a ſtrength he had promiſed to yeild unto, an authority he had promiſed to obey.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa. 45.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Ask of me,</hi> nay, command ye me. The Lord did according to the ſaying of <hi>Moſes;</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaying of the Lord, had been but equall: But, that the Lord ſhould doe according to <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaying, is wonderfully comfortable. In <hi>Joſhuah's</hi> time, touching Sunne and Moon ſtanding ſtill, he hearkened to the voyce of a man. Prayer will over-rule God to any thing for our good;<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.44. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.18, 19. Rom. 8.</note> It will bow down his eare, It will pull his hand out of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, the ſword out of his ſheath againſt his enemies, put it up again when drawn againſt his people. The Lord is at the call of his peoples pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, will fulfill the deſires of thoſe that feare him. It is the work of Gods own holy Spirit made in heaven, therefore true: faithfull prayer never was, never ſhall be loſt. Though God hide himſelfe in a cloud, this will ſcatter the cloud, it will pierce the heavens and fetch God down. If we wraſtle with God by prayer, we ſhall prevaile. Hath not much been done with God in theſe warres by this weapon? may not more alſo be done? O pray, pray, pray.</p>
               <p>Experience of Gods former favours ſhewed to perſons,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> families, the kingdome, which may encourage all to truſt him upon triall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> fought with a Lyon, and a Beare, and God delivered him
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116086:28"/>from the danger of both, Therefore will alſo out of the hand of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtine.<note place="margin">1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.36.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This encouraged <hi>Paul</hi> for time to come to relye on Gods help, having had former experience, and preſent ſupportment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, thou haſt been favourable to the Land: Ergo,</hi> wilt be.<note place="margin">Pſa. 85. Pſa. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Fathers truſted in thee, and were delivered.</hi> If we truſt in him, we alſo ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. But: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What God doth at one time, he can doe at another: Therefore he puts out himſelfe in his greatneſſe, in his goodneſſe, that his people might truſt in him, at all times.</p>
               <p>God in his juſtice may leave the land deformed; but in his mercy refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, becauſe he hath given his people a taſte of the firſt fruits already.</p>
               <p>Men relye on a friend, that hath never failed them in any extremity.<note place="margin">Pſa. 116.1.</note> 
                  <hi>I will love the Lord,</hi> (there is good cauſe) <hi>becauſe he heard my voyce, he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined his eare, therefore will I call upon him while I live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where Beggars ſpeed well, they will come again. Can you blame them for it? There is no particular perſon but hath experience that he hath his proper portion in the hope of the kingdomes publick peace.</p>
               <p>The great ſufferings and oppreſſions of Gods people,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doore</hi> 1 Pſal. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> foreſhewes Gods help is at hand. <hi>Now for the oppreſsion of the poore, and ſighing of the needy, I will up, ſaith the Lord, I will ſet him at liberty whom the wicked have ſnared. Thou will keep and preſerve him.</hi> Gods tongue hath ſpoken it, his hand will perform it. <hi>God is our hope and ſtrength, and help in troubles, ready to be found.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.1. Verſ. 8. Verſ. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Come and behold the workes of the Lord, what deſolations he hath made in the earth.</hi> In the next words is added, <hi>He maketh warres to ceaſe unto the ends of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wonderfull deſolations uſher in the ceſſation of Warres in the world. <hi>Be ſtill, and know that I am God,</hi> and know how and when,<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> to croſſe and cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, the cruelty of the enemies of my people; <hi>I am the Lord of Hoſts. Out of the deep places have I called unto thee, O Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 130. Pſal. 140.12. Pſa. 146.7</note>
               </p>
               <p>Mans greateſt hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liation is a ſigne of Gods preſent ſalvation. <hi>I know that the Lord will avenge the afflicted, and help the poore, the Lord looſeth the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, he executeth juſtice for the appreſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though he try their patience a while, yet will not faile of his promiſe made to his people, and of his juſtice toward his enemies.</p>
               <p>Conſider his authority, his fidelity mentioned in the former verſe:<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>He made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and all that therein is, which keepeth his fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for ever.</hi> If God from time to time hath relieved the oppreſſed, he will doe ſo ſtill. But he hath done ſo: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, <hi>Bleſſed is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe hope is in the Lord his God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116086:29"/>The <hi>Aihenians</hi> in their greateſt dangers by ſea, caſt forth <hi>ſacram Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> the ſacred Anchor of hope, in hope of help from ſome ſupream pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when all other hopes falled them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Look unto me yee priſoners of Hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Rubbiſh of Popery and Humane Traditions,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> begun already to be caſt forth, that place may be made for Gods building. <hi>Shall I bring to the Birth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa 66.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ch. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and not cauſe to bring forth, ſaith the Lord? Shall I cauſe to bring forth, and ſhut the womb? Who art thou great Mountain before Zerubbabel, Thou ſhalt be a plain, and be ſhall bring forth the head ſtone thereof with ſhouting, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Grace, Grace, unto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> repreſented Chriſt, and the Jewes were thought as nothing in compariſon of their adverſaries, which were as a great Mountain; yet the faith of the godly ſhall be able to remove this mountain, and caſt it into the Sea.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſe 9.</note> The hands of <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> have laid the foundation of this Houſe, his hands alſo ſhall finiſh it, the hand of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall protect him in it.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſe 10.</note> They are checked in the next verſe, that <hi>deſpiſe the day of ſmall things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Antichriſt hath been put from his out works in <hi>Scotland</hi> already, and ſhall he not be frighted from his in works in <hi>England</hi> too? Doctrine and Diſcipline have been long deſired, that there ſhould be a reformation of them in the Land, and why may not this be the time for it? Enemies have pretended a deſire of reformation, (as I have ſhewed before) in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face in the Liturgie for <hi>Aſhwedneſday</hi> Service; and ſhall not friends to their uttermoſt power endeavour it? And will not God bleſſe, hath he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready much bleſſed to a ſucceſsfull growth, their endeavours herein?</p>
               <p>Should ſuch a thing as godly Diſcipline be almoſt an hundred yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe deſired, and never all that time endeavoured? Shall it now be proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and ſhall it not be brought to be perfection? Men pray for it, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters preach for it, the Parliament pleads for it, Souldiers fight for it, and all good men (as on this day) faſt for it. May not this devill by faſting and prayer be caſt forth?</p>
               <p>Shew me any place in the whole Bible, where any people in the act of humiliation,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 7.3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 8.18.</note> were given up to be deſtroyed. Many places manifeſt, that for their humiliation they ſhall eſcape judgements, <hi>Ahab,</hi> the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> were preſerved.</p>
               <p>The Unity and Fervency of ſo many of Gods faithfull Miniſters,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>18</hi>
                  </note> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and preaching with unanimous conſent in affection (notwithſtanding ſome differences in opinions in matter of Diſcipline) for the peace of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We read of <hi>Prolomeus Philodelphus,</hi> King of Egypt, that he cauſed the ſeventy Bible to be interpreted by ſevnty Interpreters; which 70. were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116086:29"/>diſpoſed of in 70 ſeverall Cells, unknown to each other, and yet they did ſo well agree in their ſeverall Tranſlations, that there was no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable difference between them, in rendring of the Text. An argument they were acted with one and the ſame Spirit.</p>
               <p>May we not be comforted, when we call to mind, that ſeventy, nay, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventie times ſeventy, yea ſeventy hundred, yea ſeventy thouſand, which bow not the knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> but on the bended knees of ſoule, doe impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the God of peace, for peace; that doe lift up their voyces like Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, (even now, whiles Trumpets lift up their voyces like Preachers) to call upon the people for pacifying Gods wrath, and to powre forth their prayers and teares to God with conſtancy, to preſerve the Goſpell of Chriſt, Lawes of the Kingdome, and Liberties of the Subject; yea though they knew not the faces, no not the names one of another, nay have never ſeen, nor ſhall ſee one another, till they meet together in Heaven; yet doe they agree and center together in what they pray for, while they are on earth, ſaying to God, <hi>Thou ſhalt ariſe, and have mercy upon Sion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 102.13.</note> 
                  <hi>for the time</hi> to favour her, yea the ſet time, <hi>is come;</hi> for thy ſervants take pleaſure in the ſtones thereof, and favour the duſt of the ſame; the more Gods Church is in miſery, the more will the faithfull ſhew their love and labour for her deliverance. <hi>Thou ſhalt weep no more,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 30.19.</note> 
                  <hi>God will be very gracious unto thee at the voyce of thy cry; when he ſhall heare it, he will anſwer thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though the Lord give you the bread of adverſity, and the water of affliction, yet ſhall not thy Teachers be removed into a corner any more; But thine eyes ſhall ſee thy Teachers, and ſhalt heare a word behind thee, &amp;c. Teachers have been turned into corners, if they return home, it argues their abode with more conſtancy; you have the word of the King of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for it, and ſhall he promiſe, and not performe?</p>
               <p>The perſevering waiting condition of the ſervants of the Lord,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> in all holy and heavenly duties, ſeale to their ſoules the infallibility of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious promiſes to be accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>From the beginning of the world men have not heard,<note place="margin">Eſa. 64.4.</note> nor underſtood with the eare, that any God hath done ſo as our God hath done to him that waiteth for him. What will he then doe to a Family, a Pariſh, a County, a Kingdome, that for many yeares have waited for him? What hath he done for ſuch a waiter? The next words wil declare;<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou didſt meet him that rejoyced in thee, remembred thee in thy wayes, that relyed on thy word, looked for thy help. I waited patiently for the Lord, and he inclined unto me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 40.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and heard my cry. He brought me alſo out of the horrible pit, out of the miry clay, and ſet my feet upon a Rocke, and ordered my goings; and he hath put in my mouth a new ſong of praiſe to our God. Many ſhall ſee it and feare, and ſhall truſt in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116086:30"/>See the many bleſſings attended on his waiting. The Lord in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven deſcended on earth, inclined to comiſerate duſt and aſhes; his body was delivered from incumbent horrible dangers, his feet ſet on a Rock, all the waves and windes could not overturn it; his goings were ordered, men or Devils could not make him ſlide, or goe out of Gods paths. His tongue had occaſion to trumpet out Gods praiſe. The wicked that ſaw it, were convicted, the godly confirmed to truſt in the Lord. Who (for his patient waiting) had delivered his ſoule from death, his eyes from teares, and his feet from falling: how (for all this) could he doe leſſe than praiſe the Lord in the land of the living. Men ſhall ſay in that day, Lo, this is our God, we have waited for him, he will ſave us. They read over their Title to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the ſame words, <hi>This is the Lord, we have waited for him.</hi> We have waited for thee in the way of thy judgements.<note place="margin">Eſay 25.9. chap. 26 8. Verſe 3. chap. 30.18</note> 
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Truſt in the Lord for ever; for in the Lord God is ſtrength (to deliver his Church) for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: yea, the Lord waits in the beginning of the verſe, to be gracious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, Bleſſed are thoſe that wait to receive mercy from him.</p>
               <p>The path of Gods preſent proceedings,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> is a pledge of his good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for future time in the kingdome.</p>
               <p>His judgements ſeeme to be judgements of expoſtulation with, rather than of extirpation of the kingdome. Though theſe dayes ſeem to be as that day the Prophet mentioned,<note place="margin">Zach. 14.6, 7.</note> wherein was no <hi>clear light,</hi> but it was <hi>dark,</hi> it was neither (quite) day nor night, but about the evening time it ſhall be light.</p>
               <p>God will at the laſt (which is with the Lord but as the length of a day) ſend a faire and cleare evening of joy and comfort to his diſtreſſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
               <p>We read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24. that God being angry with <hi>Moſes</hi> for not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing his ſons, it came to paſſe by the way in the Inne, the Lord met him, and ſought to kill him; Sought to kill him? 'Tis ſtrange, Did God ſeek to kill him, and not kill him? Speak Lord, ſpeak to the fire, and it ſhall with fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhings conſume him; to the aire, and with peſtilent vapours choake him; to the waters, and with deluges it ſhall overwhelme him; to the earth, and with yawning chops it ſhall devoure him.</p>
               <p>Well, the meaning is, God ſought to kill him, that is, in ſome outward viſible manner, whereof <hi>Moſes</hi> was apprehenſive, God manifeſted his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt him, that ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> might have notice, and leaſure to divert his anger, by removing the cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p>He that ſaid to us, <hi>Seek and ye ſhall find,</hi> doth himſelfe ſeek and not find: And good reaſon; for he ſought with an intent not to find.</p>
               <p>Thus may we ſay, God for theſe many yeares ſought to deſtroy the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116086:30"/>Kingdome, manifeſting an unwilling-willingneſſe, if men in any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time will take up the matter, and compound the difference by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The loving Father ſhakes the Rod over the Child, not with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to beat him, but to make him beg pardon. Such hitherto hath been the Lords dealing with our Nation, that he even courts and wooes us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, as loath to puniſh us, if we would underſtand the voyce of the Rod, and why it is ſhaken over us.</p>
               <p>At what time, the Lord threatneth to pluck up, root out,<note place="margin">Mich. 6.9. Jer. 18.8.</note> and to deſtroy it, <hi>If this Nation againſt whom I have pronounced, turn from their wickedneſſe, I will repent</hi> (appearing ſo to mans judgement) <hi>of the plague I thought to bring upon them</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If men waſh their hands and hearts in teares of repentance,<note place="margin">Deut. 21.7.</note> (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the blood of the Heifer) all the blood that hath been, or ſhall be ſhed in theſe warres, it ſhall never be laid to their charge by the Lord. If thou make Conſcience thy Caſtle, let Drummes beat, Trumpets ſound, Pikes puſh, Bullets flye, Cannons roare, Death, Warres, Devils, doe their worſt, thy life is hid with God, and thou ſhalt be in ſafety.</p>
               <p>Thus have I brought you to twenty ſeverall Doores, and have a little o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened them, that you looking into the roomes, might have ſome light of comfort (even on this day, and in this formerly ſorrowfull place,) for the good ſucceſſe of the kingdomes cauſe: I have a few more doores to lead you to, but I muſt be ſpeedy in my paſſage by them, and give you leave but to peep into them, whiles your ears attend my tongue.</p>
               <p>The Saints ſorrow for the Churches miſeries,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> and love for her proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <p>Where theſe duties are performed, great dignities are peomiled.<note place="margin">Iſa. 66, 10, 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Rejoyce ye with Jeruſalem, and be glad with her, all ye that love her. Rejoyce for joy with her, all ye that mourn for her, that ye may ſuck and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of her conſolations, that ye may milk out, and be delighte I with the brightneſſe of her glory; becauſe I will extend peace over her like a floud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Peace, proſperity ſhall come ſpeedily, and in great abundance. <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem: They ſhall proſper that love thee.</hi> What's added?<note place="margin">Pſ. 122.6,</note> 
                  <hi>Peace be within thy walles, and proſperity within thy palaces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe duties enjoyned by the Lord, and practiſed by his people up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his command, and ſhall not he bleſſe his own commanded meanes?</p>
               <p>God bids remember thoſe that are in bonds, as if we were bound with them, elſe we cannot have a fellow feeling of their miſeries.</p>
               <p>Surely ſuch precepts have obliged many to weep in ſecret, watch, faſt, and pray in publick for the Churches miſeries, as if they had been their owne.</p>
               <p>It's Gods own cauſe; and can that ever miſcarry?<note place="margin">Doore <hi>22</hi>
                  </note> Hath not he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116086:31"/>it with an high hand, and ſtretched out arme in all ages?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Keep not ſilence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 83.1. Verſ 5.</note> 
                  <hi>O God;</hi> implying, it's as eaſie for God to huſh all wars, as it is for man to ſpeak. <hi>Thine enemies make a tumult, and hate thee.</hi> They have conſulted in heart, and made a league againſt thee.</p>
               <p>Hath not God pleaded the cauſe of his Saints, as if he and they were one?<note place="margin">Pſa. 35.1.</note> Elſe <hi>David</hi> would not have been ſo bold with him, ſaying, <hi>Plead my cauſe, O God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Joſhuahs</hi> time the Lord fought for Iſrael,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 10.14.</note> 'twas his owne cauſe, made therefore the Sun and Moon ſtand ſtill untill the people avenged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their enemies.</p>
               <p>In his own cauſe he hearkened to the voyce of a man, but in an evill cauſe will regard voyce of many <hi>Johs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 9.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Samuels, Daniels, Angels. Saul, Saul, Why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> in my members on earth, now I am in heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be not afraid</hi> (ſaid the propheticall Levite unto <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) <hi>for this great multitude;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 20 15.</note> 
                  <hi>for the battell is not yours, but Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Dragon and his Angels fought againſt <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels;<note place="margin">Rev. 12.7, 8.</note> but the Dragon and his Angels were caſt out of heaven unto the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they fought againſt <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels.</p>
               <p>Chriſt hath overcome the World,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>23</hi>
                  </note> Death, Devill and ſhall theſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him again?<note place="margin">Iohn 16.33. Col. 2.15. Rev. 17.14</note> It's incredible, impoſſible. <hi>Be ye of good comfort, in me ye ſhall have peace, I have over come the world.</hi> He hath openly triumphed over them on his Croſſe. This Lamb hath overcome all Lions: Can Satan be ſtronger than God?</p>
               <p>The efficacie of Chriſt his prayer:<note place="margin">Doore <hi>24</hi>
                  </note> He was heard on earth, and ſhall he not be heard in heaven,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33 1 Pet. 3.14.</note> making interceſſion for his people? Who is he that will harm you, if ye follow that which is good? Who harme us? wicked ones will: Yet bleſſed are you if ye ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake: Feare not their feare, nor be ye troubled.</p>
               <p>The conviction and converſion of Adverſaries,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>25</hi>
                  </note> God enlightning them to ſee what they did not ſee before.</p>
               <p>It is beyond the thoughts and expectation of man, thae the Lord <hi>Inche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin,</hi> ſeduced by the Jeſuitical faction, ſhould be changed from a deſtroyer, to Champion for God, and a preſerver of his cauſe.</p>
               <p>The many cries,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>26</hi>
                  </note> prayers, teares, of Fathers, Children, Widowes, for vengeance.</p>
               <p>Doth not the Lord heare their cries, and know their ſorrowes? The Lord heard the voyce of the Lad <hi>Iſhmael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 3.7. Gen. 21.17. Pſa. 146.9,</note> weeping before him; and will he not heare the voyce of thouſands of Children for their parents, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents for their children, wives for their husbands, and friends for friends? He relieveth the Fatherleſſe and Widowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116086:31"/>In whom can the Fatherleſſe finde mercy, but in him?<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3. Luke 18.7</note> If an unrighteous Judge did the importune Widow juſtice againſt her adverſary, ſhall not God avenge his elect, that cry day and night unto him?</p>
               <p>The cry of the multiplicity of the blood that hath been ſhed.<note place="margin">Doore <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Shall not the blood of ſo many Saints call for vengeance,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10 Rev. 6.10.</note> when the blood of one <hi>Abel</hi> cryed unto the Lord, and he heard it. The ſoules of the Saints ſlaine cry, <hi>Doſt thou not avenge our blood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Groans are regiſtred, teares botled, and ſhall not blood be booked? Did God enquire for one <hi>Abel?</hi> will he not for thouſands?</p>
               <p>The Relation of God towards his Church.<note place="margin">Doore <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>God ſayth, he is worſe than an Infidell that provides not for his family.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> Is not he a Father? And will a Father give ſtones to children that ask bread? He is to his Church a Husband, a Maſter, a Captain, a King, Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, Creator, Redeemer, wiſe Builder. He is a Sun and a Shield, hath his Rod and his Staffe, both for direction and preſervation.</p>
               <p>The great rage of Satan ſheweth that his time is but ſhort.<note place="margin">Doore <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>When the Devil was to be caſt forth out of the dumb,<note place="margin">Rev. 12.12 Mat. 9.22.26.</note> he caſts him into the fire, and into the water, and rent him ſoare, cryed, and then came out of him. Violent things continue not long in extremity, eſpecially ſuch ſhowers of blood.</p>
               <p>The many differences between forraigne nations,<note place="margin">Doore <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> who would have joyned hand in hand againſt the Kingdome, had they not been ſet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the eares in their own lands.</p>
               <p>This is none of the leaſt of Gods mercies to our nation at this time, they having enough to doe at home, have the leſſe leaſure to be imployed, as the Devils and Popes Armour-bearers abroad.</p>
               <p>The prevention of many inconveniences which might enſue.<note place="margin">Doore <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Some godly ones might put forth their hands to wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſa, 125.3.</note> if the rod of the wicked ſhould long lye on the lot of the righteous.</item>
                  <item>2. That the wicked might not deny Gods power, providence, juſtice, which they ſee executed here on earth.</item>
                  <item>3. Truth of the Scriptures may not bee queſtioned, <hi>Tribulation bringeth forth patience; patience, experience; experience, hope.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 5.4</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Now lay all theſe conſiderations together, that have been mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and I beleeve they will adminiſter joy in the times of ſorrow, and keep up mens hearts leſſe to doubt the ſucceſſe of the common cauſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Conſidering God is a God of power, able to finiſh what he hath begun.</item>
                  <item>2. It ſtands with his wiſdome, the foundation laid to perfect his building.</item>
                  <item>3. God is the God of order, what confuſion elſe would be?</item>
                  <item>4. Kindneſſe had been unkindneſſe. Better to have had no cluſter of grapes,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116086:32"/>than not to be brought into <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Weak ones would ſuſpect God uſed ſome ſtratagem to draw men out, as the men of <hi>Ai,</hi> to deſtroy them, or as to gather Bees and to burn them.</item>
                  <item>6. They would doubt, God would not doe as much for his people now, as he hath done heretofore. <hi>Our Fathers truſted in him, and were delivered;</hi> but we have truſted in him, and are not delivered.</item>
                  <item>7. Gods friends would put forth their hands to wickedneſſe.</item>
                  <item>8. His enemies blaſphemies, boaſtings, cruelties, would be the greater. They would endeavour to build Babels to ſcale (if poſſible) the very walts of heaven.</item>
                  <item>9. God ſpared the kingdome for a long ſeaſon, when ſin was committed, and with greedineſſe acted;<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.30.</note> and will he not ſpare it now, when ſinne is confeſſed, lamented, and many ſtand up in the gap, to turn away his wrath, and reform impieties, according to his deſire and promiſe?</item>
                  <item>10. The courage of the Parliament, Commanders, Captaines, Souldiers, beyond ordinary expectation, naturall Relations, carrying Gods Ark towards <hi>Bethſhemeſh,</hi> their wives, children, houſes, lands, goods, liberties, lives, being not deere unto them, doe all confirme our hearts in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Lord, that his help is at hand, to deliver the Nation from ſlavery and Popery.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I beſeech you by the many mercies of God, that have been daily manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and infallibly expected, to lay out your ſelves, to give up your bodies, ſpirits, eſtates, your All, for your ſelves, poſterity, Cities, and people of God.</p>
               <p>It was dying <hi>Joſhuahs</hi> argument to the Iſraelites, to move them to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant obedience to Gods commandements, that they had experimentall knowledge in their hearts, that nothing failed of all the good things that the Lord had promiſed to them, all came to paſſe: And have wee not as great a portion, participation in Gods promiſes and performances as the Iſraelites had?</p>
               <p>We may ſay of Gods mercies to Iſrael, and England, as one ſpake of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and <hi>Tully.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Cicero effecit, ne Demoſthenes eſſes ſolus Orator,</l>
                  <l>Demoſthenes, ne Cicero primus foret.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The Iſraelites were the cauſe, we could not be the firſt people whome God did ſo extraordinarily bleſſe and favour.</p>
               <p>But we are the cauſe that they could not boaſt themſelves to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people in Gods love.</p>
               <p>And if Gods mercies in any age, for height, length, depth, breadth, might be boaſted of, rejoyced in, then in our dayes, in this Parliament, in
<pb facs="tcp:116086:32"/>theſe warres, where good is fetcht out of evill, light out of darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>And if theſe things will be marvellous in the eares of all poſterity, ſhall they not in our hearts, before whoſe eyes the ſame have been accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed?</p>
               <p>Wherefore I conclude as I began, (being high time to take my worke off the Loome) <hi>Why halt ye ſo long between two opinions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Baal be God,</hi> then follow him; ſo ſhall you fall from ſin the Suburbs, into Hell it ſelfe, the place, portion, expectation of all curſed neutralizing <hi>Balaaks,</hi> for whom are reſerved torments which are endleſſe, eaſeleſſe, and remedileſſe.</p>
               <p>If the Lord be God, then follow him, ſo ſhall you come to ſee him, that is inviſible, and ſhall change the ſociety of men for Angels, Earth for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the company of Lions for fellowſhip with the Lamb for ever.</p>
               <p>Where ſhall be all light without any darkneſſe, truth without error, joy without ſorrow, health without ſickneſſe, liberty without reſtraint, peace without perturbation, eternity without end; where the Quire of Angels ſhall be muſick to our eares, where the fight of God ſhall be the object to our eyes, where the joyes of heaven ſhall be the poſſeſſion of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>Unto the hearing of which Angellicall muſick, unto the beholding of which beatificall viſion, unto the poſſeſſion of which celeſtiall joyes, the Lord that is Author of all, vouchſafe to bring us all, &amp; let all Gods people ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi> And let the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe words are <hi>Yea and Amen,</hi> put to his hand and ſeale, and ſay, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have now done for ſpeaking, you have now done for hearing; his Chaire and Pulpit is in heaven that muſt perſwade you to put in practice thoſe things which I have delivered in precept: which that he may doe, unto him let us pray.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Soli Deo laus.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
